<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-06-30T20:54:13+03:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">TheHope.org</title><subtitle>TheHope.org Visions for renewed Israel the Heavenly Jerusalem and the Holographic Temple  </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Appendix 3-C: Lekh-lekha Portion: How many potential members has Israel?</title><link href="/blog/2010/03/12/appendix-3-c-lekh-lekha-portion-how-many-potential-members-has-israel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Appendix 3-C: Lekh-lekha Portion: How many potential members has Israel?" /><published>2010-03-12T07:05:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-03-12T07:05:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/2010/03/12/appendix-3-c-lekh-lekha-portion-how-many-potential-members-has-israel</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2010/03/12/appendix-3-c-lekh-lekha-portion-how-many-potential-members-has-israel.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;lekh-lekha-portion-how-many-potential-members-has-israel&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lekh-lekha Portion: How many potential members has Israel?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Yitzḥaq Ḥayut-Man&lt;/strong&gt; _ Genesis Lekh-lekhah with its Haftarah.10.2012 22:52_&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;|   |
| — |&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;|
| — |&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Haftarah for the Lekh-lekha portion refers to Abraham as encouragement to beget the world's leading, and even largest, nation. From this perspective we survey the numbers that appear in the Parashah and find that the Twelve-fold Nation of Israel is potentially the largest of all nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lekh-lekha&quot;&gt;Lekh-Lekha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;portion&quot;&gt;Portion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##
(Gen. 12:1-17:27)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-many-potential-members&quot;&gt;How many Potential Members&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;does-the-nation-of-israel-have&quot;&gt;Does the Nation of Israel have?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Torah portion (&lt;em&gt;Parashah&lt;/em&gt;, which is read publicly on the Saturday) of  &lt;strong&gt;Lekh-lekha&lt;/strong&gt;  (Gen. 12:1-17:27) has many events: 1) the command to Avram to go to the Land, 2) Avram's descent to Egypt and the events between Avram, Saray and Pharaoh, 3) Avram's separation from Lot, 4) the war of the kings and Avram's victory, 5) the covenant by the divided offerings, 6) the birth of Yishmạ'el, and 7) the promise concerning Yitzḥaq (Isaac) and the covenant of circumcision. Each of these has gathered hips of exegeses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps surprisingly, the Haftarah (section from the Books of the Prophets read after the &lt;em&gt;Parashah&lt;/em&gt;) ties with the case of the kings, and this connection is only hinted – but from it we can learn more what the goal of the selection of Avram-Abraham was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Haftarah is from Isaiah (40:27- 41:16) and it is addressed to Israel: “But thou, Yisra'el, art my servant, Ya'ạqov whom I have chosen, the seed of Avraham my friend” (40:8). This is, in fact, the only mention of Avraham in the Haftarah, and even here not by a direct mention – but the mention that Ya'ạqov was of Avraham's seed, and Ya'ạqov (and not Abraham) is the founder of the Nation of Israel. Clearly, this is not for this mention that the Haftarah was selected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Haftarah contains a verse that, though it does not name Avraham explicitly, does hint at him: “who raised up one from the east whom righteousness met wherever he set his foot, gave the nations before him, and made him rule over kings…” (41:2). Who is that 'man of righteousness' who came from the East and overcame rules and kings? According to Genesis, this was Avram-Avraham, who started his journey from Ur-Kasdim in the East and overcame the four kings. The Haftarah gathers the meanings of the events of the &lt;em&gt;Parashah&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Lekh lekhah&lt;/em&gt; in order to give the nation of Israel confidence and credence. The trials of Avraham are a model for the situation of the People of Israel, and the connection concerns military and foreign affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The successful contention of Avram with the kings does not resemble his contention with Pharaoh, an affair that gave Avram riches, but not honor (the man of righteousness and generosity in this Parashah is in fact Pharaoh).  It is also not only the contention with the four kings of the East but with ten kings – the four kings, the five local kings who were also wicked (see Rashi's interpretation of their names) as well as with the mysterious figure or “Malkitzedek king of Shalem… a priest of the Highest God” (Gen. 14:18). Here is was Avram who acts with justice and generosity; he relinquished his share of the great booty, whereas to the priest-king he gave “a tithe of everything”. This can be interpreted as a tithe from the booty, but it is also possible to understand as a tithe from everything that Avram had – in thus perhaps penance for the riches he gained by delivering his wife to Pharaoh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number Ten returns later in the Covenant In-Between the Pieces, in which Avram received the fourth of the seven divine promises that he received in the Parashah of Lekh-lekha. His seed is promised to receive the country of ten nations: the Qeny, Qenizzi, Qadmony, Ḥitti, Perizzi, the Refa'im, the Emori, Kena'ạni, Girgashi and Yevusi. (Interestingly, of all these ten peoples, the Parashah counts only “and the Kena'ạni and the Perizzi then in the land” (Gen. 13:7), and does not mention these other nations, and in other lists of the people of Kena'ạn only six or seven nations are mentioned.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the course of the portion, another number is mentioned – 318. These three hundred and eighteen were “his trained servants, born in his own house” (14:14), yet not his biological sons (as the overall theme of the Parashah is the sterility of Avram and Saray). When he was circumcised, he was already “Avraham” (meaning “father of multitudes”) he also “took Yishma'el his son, and all that were born in his house, and all that were bought with his money, every male among the men of Avraham's house; and circumcised the flesh of their foreskin” (17:20) - which obviously included those 318.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important number that appears in the Parashah is included in the blessing for Ishmael – even though he would not be included in the blessings to Yitzḥaq: “And as for Yishmạ'el, I have heard thee; behold, I have blessed him, and will make him fruitful, and will multiply him exceedingly, twelve princes (&lt;em&gt;nesi'im&lt;/em&gt;) shall he beget, and I will make him a great nation” (17:20). This blessing for a nation of twelve parties, which was first given to Yishmạ'el, would later be given also to Abraham's grandson, Ya'ạqov-Israel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Haftarah brings Abraham as a model for Israel, because of two reasons – his military daring and his belief (albeit shaky at times) that he – old and childless as he was - will still have offspring as numerous as the sand of the earth and the stars in the heavens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this, there issue a few conclusions concerning the Nation of Israel as the Servant of God - which is also “a Servant Nation”8 for all humankind – as it is written in the beginning of the Parashah “in thee shall all the families of the earth be blessed” (12:3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At present, as in the time of Isaiah, we are under the feeling that we are a small nation that comprises solely of “The Jewish People” (&lt;em&gt;Ạm Yisra'el&lt;/em&gt;), whose survival is under threat. The mention of Abraham in these Parashah and Haftarah come to give encourage to Israel. Israel is not an exclusively the nation of Jews, but a twelve-part nation whose components identify themselves with the promises to Abraham. The picturesque promise of “look now towards heaven, and count the stars, if thou be able to count them; and he said to him, so shall thy seed be” (15:5). This count is not so clear mathematically – does it concern only the stars seen with naked eyes (a few thousands), or the number of stars in the galaxy (tens of billions) or in all the billions of galaxies (possibly more than all the grains of sand upon earth, 12:16). A more precise estimate is contained in the hope of Moshe (Moses) for the People of Israel “The Lord your God has multiplied you, and, behold, you are this day like the stars of heaven for multitude. The Lord God of your fathers may add to you a thousand times so many as you are, and bless you, as He has promised you” (Deut. 1:10-11). About 600,000 men who exited from Egypt multiplied by thousand means well over 600 million - and since these 600,000 included only combat-age men, the total actually reaches some two billion (also, if we calculate the over 6 million contemporary Israeli Jews times 318 of joiners - as in the case of Abraham and his household - we get about two billion). Clearly such a Nation of Israel is not identified with only “The Jewish People”, but includes much beyond that, the potential is among all the people who are affected by the message of the Hebrew Bible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Article viewed  &lt;strong&gt;1807&lt;/strong&gt;  times between 27.10.2012 – 1.2.2019&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Lekh-lekha Portion: How many potential members has Israel?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Appendix 1-A: The Tree of Life Pattern in the Kabbalah</title><link href="/regenesis/2010/03/12/appendix-1-a-the-tree-of-life-pattern-in-the-kabbalah.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Appendix 1-A: The Tree of Life Pattern in the Kabbalah" /><published>2010-03-12T07:05:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-03-12T07:05:00+02:00</updated><id>/regenesis/2010/03/12/appendix-1-a-the-tree-of-life-pattern-in-the-kabbalah</id><content type="html" xml:base="/regenesis/2010/03/12/appendix-1-a-the-tree-of-life-pattern-in-the-kabbalah.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thehope.org/regenesis/appendix-1-a-the-tree-of-life-pattern-in-the-kabbalah/&quot;&gt;https://www.thehope.org/regenesis/appendix-1-a-the-tree-of-life-pattern-in-the-kabbalah/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/tree-of-life_436x640.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;drawing&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tree of Life by David Friedman, Tsfat&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;appendix-the-tree-of-the-sefirot-as-the-tree-of-life-the-2d-diagram-as-projection-of-the-5-d-world-of-sefer-tezirah-the-parallel-scheme-of-inter-human-communications&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Appendix: The Tree of the Sefirot as the Tree of Life; The 2D diagram as projection of the 5-D world of Sefer Tezirah; The parallel scheme of inter-human communications.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pattern of &lt;strong&gt;“the Tree of the &lt;em&gt;Sefirot&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/strong&gt; (“The Holy Tree” in the Zohar and commonly called “The Tree of Life”) is no doubt the most famous topic of Kabbalah teachings. Most books on the market that treat the Kabbalah deal only with this Tree, and the first knowledge of novices to the Kabbalah usually identifies it with the Tree of the Sefirot. In the following we shall bring the essential terms and their graphic expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pattern describes the flow of the &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;yut&lt;/strong&gt; – “vital intelligence” – that maintains all the worlds – and therefore is considered as the picture of “The Tree of Life” (&lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;yim&lt;/strong&gt;). This is a pattern of 32 elements. The number 32 is marked in Hebrew by the two letters Lamed (Gematria value 30) and &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;yt&lt;/strong&gt; (Gematria value 2), which together spell &lt;strong&gt;L&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;V&lt;/strong&gt; (לב) – namely “&lt;strong&gt;Heart&lt;/strong&gt;”. So this is a picture of the “Heart” that maintains all the worlds. This is an abstract pattern, essentially graphic, of what is called in mathematics “graph” – points or vertices that are connected by some lines or conduits.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; According to the instructions given in the &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;efe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;r Y&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ẓir&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;, where the term “Sefirot” was first mentioned, what are entailed are ten vertices (called “Sefirot”) that are interlinked by 22 lines of conduits – &lt;strong&gt;Ẓ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;norot&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These 22 lines are identified in Sefer Yezirah with the 22 Hebrew (&lt;strong&gt;Ịvriot&lt;/strong&gt;) letters (&lt;strong&gt;Ot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;yot&lt;/strong&gt;, signals – &lt;strong&gt;Otot&lt;/strong&gt; or symbols for kinds of transfer – &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ạv&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;), which are designated in Sefer Yeẓirah to three groups: (1) of three “Mother Letters”; (2) of seven “double letters”; and (3) of twelve “simple letters”. Thereafter there was developed in the Kabbalah a two-dimensional diagram (which has a few versions) of a graph with 10 vertices that are connected by three horizontal connections, seven vertical connections, and twelve diagonal connections (see figure 1 below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;TBA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this pattern there is a distinction between the Right side (or “column” - &lt;strong&gt;Ạmud&lt;/strong&gt;), Left side, and the Middle (and thereby it actually accommodates the Taoist “Yin-Yang” pattern). In general, the Right side is related in the Kabbalah to Mercy, Grace and greatness – that is, generalization; whereas the Left side is related rigor and judgment – namely detailing, and the Middle column is the integration of the opposing qualities. This pattern also contains vertical distinction between Up and Down, distinguishing seven vertical levels (and thereby it also accommodates the Hinduist pattern of the seven Chakras). The resulting pattern is a clearly anthropomorphic figure, which designates also the structure of Adam Qadmon (the primordial human pattern).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According the &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ḥ El&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;hu&lt;/strong&gt; discourse in the &lt;strong&gt;Tiq&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;q&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;une Zoh&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt;, the pattern of the Tree of the Sefirot is a fractal pattern. It can be seen as a pattern that repeats in each of the four worlds that we’ve mentioned above, and even within each of the ten Sephirot (and then that sephirah is called “&lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;rẓuf&lt;/strong&gt;” - facial configuration). Also the pattern of connections between the worlds can be seen in it. In this context, the three supernal Sefirot, &lt;strong&gt;K&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;k&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Bin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; , pertain to the hidden domain of “&lt;strong&gt;Ọl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;m h&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ba&lt;/strong&gt;” - in which may be found the worlds of “&lt;strong&gt;Ad&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;m Q&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dmon&lt;/strong&gt;” (&lt;em&gt;Keter&lt;/em&gt;), “&lt;strong&gt;Ọl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;m h&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aẓilut&lt;/strong&gt;” (&lt;em&gt;Ḥokhman&lt;/em&gt;) and “&lt;strong&gt;Ọl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;m h&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bri&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ah&lt;/strong&gt;” (&lt;em&gt;Binah&lt;/em&gt;). The seven lower Sefirot, which contain the six Sefirot of &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;s&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;d&lt;/strong&gt;, Gevurah (or &lt;strong&gt;Din&lt;/strong&gt;), &lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;f&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;er&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt; (or &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mim&lt;/strong&gt;), &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ẓ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Hod&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Yesod&lt;/strong&gt; – are regarded as “the Six Sides” of “&lt;em&gt;Ọlam haYeẓirah&lt;/em&gt;” together with the lowest Sefirah of Malkhut – which pertains to &lt;strong&gt;Ọl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;m h&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Ạs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;si&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;. In any case, in whichever level or detail that the diagram is used, it allows a dynamic Systemic perception of whichever topic is studied. The investigated topic is perceived not as a given and isolated object but as a dynamic balance that is derived and created from a system of mutual relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I see it, the “Tree of Life” pattern of the Kabbalah is a surface (2D) projection diagram of the five-dimensional (5D) hyperspace described in Sefer Yeẓirah (where the highest Sefirah, &lt;em&gt;Keter&lt;/em&gt;, is also the connection to many additional dimensions). The six lower Sefirot (from &lt;em&gt;Ḥesed&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Yesod&lt;/em&gt;) represent the three-dimensional space of the three perpendicular axes: Left-Right, Forward-Backward (or North-South, East West). And Up-Down. The higher Sefirot represent dimensions that are “beyond” this space (hyperspace), as dimensions perpendicular to the ordinary dimensions, dimensions of time and of soul. Sefer Yeẓirah regards the six lower Sefirot as a three-dimensional cubical space or “world” (&lt;strong&gt;Ọl&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;), and the two additional dimensions as the dimension of Time (either as “Year” – &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;ha&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; – of the axis of Beginning-Conclusion); and an additional dimension of “Soul” (&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;f&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;s&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;) – a moral dimension of the axis of “Good-Evil”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(“The Gate of Unification {&lt;em&gt;Sha’ạr haYiḥud&lt;/em&gt;}” of Rabbi Dov-Baer Schneurson, “the Middle Rebbe” of Chabad, analyses the three supernal Sefirot – &lt;em&gt;Hokhmah, Binah&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;em&gt;Da’ạt&lt;/em&gt; – each one according to depth, width ad length. The depth of a lower one is the length of the one above it. This way is formed a multidimensional array by which Da’at (Knowledge) is examined. The first Chabad Rebbe, Rabbi Shneur-Zalman of Liadi, explained the 32 “Paths of Wisdom” as the edges of what is nowadays called a 4-dimensional hypercube,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; whose projection over the surface of the earth are the twelve border lines between the twelve tribes of Israel.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the cybernetic perspective that I have been studying,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the pattern of the Tree of the Sefirot is just the pattern of the holistic scheme of a fruitful multi-level conversation between any two psychological or collective-cultural entities, a pattern that ought to be the holistic paradigm for all the social sciences – see figure 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;TBA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this pattern, the two side pillars (or figures) are the psychological representation of the two participants - each one of three levels, that accord with the Kabbalah terms of “&lt;strong&gt;Nefesh, Ru’aḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;strong&gt;Neshamah&lt;/strong&gt;”, and are defined in cognitive cybernetics as “Concepts (Con N), Memories (Mem N) and Identities (P. Individual N) of each participant – whereas the four junctions on the middle pillar are the means in which the commonalities are built: (1) the Common Ground or the material means common to their activities; (2) the domain of Agreements, or common norms, that control the behavior of the participants; (3) the domain of Understandings that might be built between them (and can change the agreements, when necessary); and (4) the domain of Realizations that stand beyond the a-priori concepts and beliefs of the two participants, but may be revealed through genuine dialogue processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-readings&quot;&gt;Further Readings:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wikipedia article: &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kabbalah&quot;&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kabbalah&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aryeh Kaplan, Sefer Yetzirah, Aronson, 1995: The Ari-Gra Space cube: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.psyche.com/psyche/cube/cube_gra.html&quot;&gt;http://www.psyche.com/psyche/cube/cube_gra.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Mathematically (topologically) speaking, this is not “a Tree Diagram” but a graph of “semi-lattice”. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Many Qabbalah texts note the connection between &lt;strong&gt;Ẓ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;nor&lt;/strong&gt; (conduit and literally “Pipe”) and its permutation of its letters – &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;a&lt;strong&gt;ẓon&lt;/strong&gt; (Will). The cause of the Creation is the Will of the infinite “Owner of the Will” (&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ạl h&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ẓon&lt;/strong&gt;) to create a finite universe, to create a void place (&lt;em&gt;Ḥalal panuy&lt;/em&gt;) devoid of divinity – and then to come in and dwell in it. “Said rabbi Shemuel bar Ami, from the beginning of the creation of the world the Holy One craved to have a partnership with the lower entities” (Midrash Genesis Rabba, part 3 para. 9), and likewise: “Let His Name be blessed forever that He leaves the higher worlds and chose the lower to dwell (shakhon) in the tabernacle (Mishkan) because of the love of Israel” (Midrash Tanḥuma vayiqra, chap. 4). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Liqqute Torah Mas’e, discourse vayered haGevul page 94a-d. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yitzhak Khayutman: The Cybernetic Basis for Human Reconstruction, Doctoral Dissertation, Brunnel University Department of Cybernetics, 1981. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Yitzhaq Hayut-Man, Ph.D</name></author><summary type="html">https://www.thehope.org/regenesis/appendix-1-a-the-tree-of-life-pattern-in-the-kabbalah/</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Appendix 1-B: Worlds &amp;amp; Multidimensions of Genesis</title><link href="/regenesis/2010/03/12/appendix-1-b-worlds-multidimensions-of-genesis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Appendix 1-B: Worlds &amp; Multidimensions of Genesis" /><published>2010-03-12T07:05:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-03-12T07:05:00+02:00</updated><id>/regenesis/2010/03/12/appendix-1-b-worlds-multidimensions-of-genesis</id><content type="html" xml:base="/regenesis/2010/03/12/appendix-1-b-worlds-multidimensions-of-genesis.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thehope.org/regenesis/appendix-1-b-worlds-multidimensions-of-genesis/&quot;&gt;https://www.thehope.org/regenesis/appendix-1-b-worlds-multidimensions-of-genesis/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/yhvh.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;drawing&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genesis as multidimensional text; Sefer Yetzirah and Parashat Bereshit; The Name of YHWH as a Multidimensional Ladder&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;worlds-and-dimensions-of-genesis&quot;&gt;Worlds and Dimensions of Genesis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the introduction and in the exegesis of the &lt;em&gt;Bereshit&lt;/em&gt; portion, we have brought the concepts of “worlds” in the Kabbalah. Here we shall try to understand the matter of these invisible spiritual worlds through the geometrical concept of “dimensions” that are perpendicular (orthogonal) to each other. It is very fashionable these days to discuss invisible higher worlds in terms of multidimensional space or hyperspace, which seems like the new thing. But in the sequel, we shall see that this approach has already been adopted in the earliest book of the Kabbalah – the “Sefer Yetzirah” (Book of Formation”) – which can be regarded as a Kabbalah interpretation of the first chapter of Genesis, and that such a multidimensional approach is employed also in the Kabbalah and &lt;em&gt;Ḥassidut&lt;/em&gt;. If so, there is also no reason to deny the possibility that this was also the pattern that was employed by the editors of the Book of Genesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of this essay is to reveal a true Torah code that is based on the five-dimensional geometry of Sefer Yetzirah as already employed in the Book of Genesis. As mentioned, Light - which appears in Genesis as the first created thing – according to current scientific view is vibrations in five-dimensional space. In general, we can discern in the scriptures two methods that mark what we nowadays characterize as “dimensions”. One method is to employ powers – the number of times a number is multiplied by itself. Thus, we shall see in the following that the name of the chosen one – Abram has Gematria value of 243, which is 3 to the fifth power (3x3x3x3x3 = 243) and thus also represents the 5-dimensional hypercube of Sefer Yetzirah (attributed by tradition to Abraham).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another method, that issues from the first is to count the powers of ten in a specific number – the units represent the first dimension (e.g. length), the tens represent the second dimension (e.g. breadth), the hundreds represent a third dimension (e.g. height) and from here it is possible to continue, where thousands already represent 4-Dimensional hyperspace, and myriads represent fifth dimension (this method is explicitly employed in many Kabbalah texts).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 60's of the 20th century Herbert Marcuse's book “One-Dimensional Man” served as a manifest for the rebel students. Marcuse used this geometrical metaphor to criticize modern consumer society that suffers from narrow consciousness and leads to life devoid of psychological and spiritual “depth”. The dimensional metaphor of consciousness was advanced by the book of Abbott Abbott “Flatland”, which describes a two-dimensional world whose residents persecute whoever raises the possibility of the existence of a three-dimensional world, and through the work of Charles Hinton, that aimed to nurture expanded consciousness that can perceive four-dimensional space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expectation and call for multidimensional awareness promise solutions to some of the contemporary world ills. The scientific revolution (“The Tree of Knowledge”) progressed in the route charted by Descartes – disjunction between the soul and the material world. It was Descartes who fixed the modern conception of using three-dimensional coordinates for the description and measurement of all the phenomena of the physical world. But in the process modern science lost just what was the really important for Descartes – namely the soul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sefer Yetzirah and Parashat Bereshit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tradition ascribes Sefer Yetzirah to the patriarch Abraham. Among modern scholars there are divergences about the time of its composition, though most agree about the range posited by Gershom Scholem: between the 2nd and 6th century C.E. (parallel to the time of the pre-Kabbalah “&lt;em&gt;Heikhalot&lt;/em&gt; literature”). Yehudah Libes, in his book “Ars Poetica in Sefer Yetsira” attributes it to the circle of the 2nd Temple in the 1st century C.E., and there are some that attribute it to the period after the appearance of Islam in the 7th century. I tend to combine the two approaches and regard the first, terse and poetical part the derivative of an esoteric inner text of the Temple scribes, whereas its expanded part, which contains the exhaustive lists  of 3, of 7 and of 12 elements, I regard as an addendum by a sixth century Jewish astrological-healer. What is pertinent for us here is the profound conception of Sefer Yetzirah of the processes of creation and formation as an esoteric explanation of the Bereshit narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In parallel with the text that opens the Book of Genesis – “In the beginning (&lt;em&gt;Bereshit&lt;/em&gt;) God (&lt;em&gt;Elohim&lt;/em&gt;) created heaven and earth” – Sefer Yetzirah starts with these words: “In thirty-two wondrous paths of wisdom – YAH, the Lord of Hosts, the God of Israel, the Living God and King of the Universe, El SHADAI, merciful and compassionate, Dweller up above, whose habitation is eternity, His Name holy - engraved and created his universe in through three &lt;em&gt;Sefarim&lt;/em&gt;: (1) Sefer (book) = writing (letters); (2) Sefor (counting) = number; (3) Sippur (telling) = speech (sounds). Ten Sefirot (numbers) made of Nothingness, Twenty-two foundation Letters”. Thus, “&lt;em&gt;Bereshit&lt;/em&gt;” is parallel to some extent to “thirty-two wondrous paths of wisdom” (much like “Elohim” parallels the above ten divine appellations in Sefer Yetzirah and the three Sefarim parallel the plenitude of “heaven and earth”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ten Sefirot are described in several ways, including: “Ten Sefirot made of Nothing (or alternatively, “of control” - &lt;em&gt;Blimah&lt;/em&gt;). Their number is Ten that have no end: The range of beginning, the range of end; The range of good, the range of evil; The range of height, the range of depth; The range of east, The range of west; The range of north, the range of south. Only Lord, God Faithful King, ruler of them all from the Residence of His Holiness to Eternity”. And likewise: “Ten Sefirot made of Nothing (or “of control”). The first: The spirit (wind) of the Living God. The second: Wind from the Spirit (wind). The third: Water from the Wind. The fourth: Fire from the Water; and Height and Depth, and East and West, and North and South” – like the five axes of expansion in the five-dimensional (5D) space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another place, the book regards the Sefirot in terms of &lt;strong&gt;Ọlam&lt;/strong&gt; , &lt;strong&gt;Shanah&lt;/strong&gt; , &lt;strong&gt;Nefesh&lt;/strong&gt; – “World, Year, Soul”. &lt;em&gt;Ọlam&lt;/em&gt;-World is the perceivable three-dimensional worlds, and it parallels the six directions enumerated above. “ &lt;strong&gt;Shanah&lt;/strong&gt; -Year” is a dimension of time that extends between “The range of beginning and the range of end”, whereas &lt;strong&gt;Nefesh&lt;/strong&gt; -Soul is an ethical dimension that sets measures between “The range of good and the range of evil”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the description the created world in Sefer Yetzirah as a hypercube of five dimensions, there emerges the primal state of the thirty-two paths (or the direction-lines), because the 4-dimensional hypercube has 32 edges, and the 5-dimensional “hyper-hypercube” has 32 vertices. This number then is not just the happenstance of the sum of the 10 digits and the 22 Hebrew letters, but is of essence and sign by itself. In fact, as we saw in the first verse of Genesis, 22 letters are the &lt;strong&gt;Miluy&lt;/strong&gt; (filling) and intermediary between two wholes (the perfect numbers of 6 and 28). In the sequel of the first chapter of Genesis appear the 10 Divine utterances as well as the 32 appearances of the name “Elohim”. In Sefer Yetzirah, the 22 letters intermediate between the two primal numerical principles of the 10 Sephirot (as the axes of five-dimensional space) and the 32 paths, which are the 32 directions in five-dimensional space: 32 – 10 = 22.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later the Kabbalah developed (or revealed) the pattern of “the Tree of the Sefirot”, or “The Tree of Life” (see appendix 1-A). This is a kind of two-dimensional schematic map of that same five-dimensional universe. The six lower “Sefirot of Construction”(from &lt;strong&gt;Ḥesed&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;Yesod&lt;/strong&gt; ) are also the six directions of three-dimensional space, corresponding to “Ọlam haYetzirah”. The three supernal Sefirot are each orthogonal to its former (from “below”) and in a higher dimension. The Sefirah of &lt;strong&gt;Binah&lt;/strong&gt; corresponds to &lt;strong&gt;Ọlam&lt;/strong&gt;** haBeri'a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;, the Sefirah of&lt;/strong&gt; Ḥokhmah&lt;strong&gt;(Wisdom) corresponds to&lt;/strong&gt;Ọlam &lt;strong&gt;**ha'Atẓilut&lt;/strong&gt; and the Sefirah of &lt;strong&gt;Keter&lt;/strong&gt; is beyond these dimensions and surrounds them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consequently, Olam haYetzirah (in which, according to the Kabbalah, the spirits {same in Hebrew as “winds”} operate) is like a 3-D world of the motion that is recorded within the four-dimensional space-time: “round and round goes the wind/spirit, and on its circuits the wind/spirit returns” (Ecclesiastes 1:6), whereas Ọlam haBeri'ah (in which operate the oversouls – &lt;strong&gt;Neshamot&lt;/strong&gt; is a kind of super-temporal five-dimensional world, as describes in Sefer Yetzirah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The five-level scale of the soul ( &lt;strong&gt;Nefesh&lt;/strong&gt; , &lt;strong&gt;Ru'aḥ&lt;/strong&gt; , &lt;strong&gt;Neshamah&lt;/strong&gt; , &lt;strong&gt;Ḥayah&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;strong&gt;Yeḥidah&lt;/strong&gt; ) of the Kabbalah is the fifth-dimension axis of Sefer Yetzirah, a dimension that is orthogonal to the four dimensions of space-time and penetrates it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Name of YHWH as a Multidimensional Ladder&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Book of Proverbs (18:10) “The Name of the Lord is a strong tower, the righteous runs into it, and is exalted”. This means that the very name &lt;strong&gt;YHWH&lt;/strong&gt; (the Tetragrammaton, the four-lettered Shem YHWH) is a kind of a tower or a ladder that stands between heaven and earth and lifts whoever contemplates it up to spiritual situation of the righteous and exalted, one who sojourns in the higher worlds. Indeed, the Name ( &lt;strong&gt;haShem&lt;/strong&gt; ) of YHWH serves in the Kabbalah as a map of the worlds – where the lower H ( &lt;strong&gt;He&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;strong&gt;ה&lt;/strong&gt; ) is the bottom edge and the top tip point of the first letter Y ( &lt;strong&gt;Yod&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;strong&gt;י&lt;/strong&gt; ) is the point of contact with the highest world. According to this fairly common practice, the lower H ( &lt;strong&gt;ה&lt;/strong&gt; ) represents the Sefirah of &lt;strong&gt;Malkhut&lt;/strong&gt; (Kingship) and the World of Action &lt;strong&gt;(Ọlam haẠsiah&lt;/strong&gt;), the Wav ( &lt;strong&gt;ו&lt;/strong&gt;** -&lt;strong&gt;with numerical value of six) represents the six Sefirot (“the Six Edges”) of the World of Formation (Ọlam haYetzirah), the upper H (&lt;/strong&gt;ה&lt;strong&gt;) represents the Sefirah of&lt;/strong&gt;Binah&lt;strong&gt;(Understanding) and the world of&lt;/strong&gt;Beri'ah&lt;strong&gt;(Formation, and also “The Maternal Face” of the Godhead), the Y (&lt;/strong&gt;Yod ** ** י&lt;strong&gt;) represents the Sefirah of&lt;/strong&gt;Ḥokhmah&lt;strong&gt;(Wisdom, and also “The Paternal Face” of the Godhead), whereas the top tip of the Y (&lt;/strong&gt;Yod ** ** י&lt;strong&gt;) represents the point of contact with the Sefirah of&lt;/strong&gt;Keter&lt;strong&gt;(Crown, which like its name implies, surrounds –&lt;/strong&gt;Koteret&lt;strong&gt;– all the worlds) and with the world of&lt;/strong&gt;Adam Qadmon** (the Primordial Image).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet the three Hebrew letters that comprise the Tetragrammaton can be conceived as representing the geometrical concepts of Point ( &lt;strong&gt;י&lt;/strong&gt; ), Line ( &lt;strong&gt;ו&lt;/strong&gt; ) and surface ( &lt;strong&gt;ה&lt;/strong&gt; ). If so, it is possible to regard the “tower” of the Name ( &lt;strong&gt;Shem&lt;/strong&gt; ) of &lt;strong&gt;YHWH&lt;/strong&gt; as constituting the geometrical representations of the letters, which combine together into the following geometrical structure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lower H ( &lt;strong&gt;ה&lt;/strong&gt; ) is the surface upon earth, upon which the tower of haShem is situated. The W ( &lt;strong&gt;ו&lt;/strong&gt; ) is conceived as the line that is perpendicular to that base surface. The upper H ( &lt;strong&gt;ה&lt;/strong&gt; ) would be regarded as a surface – namely two dimensions – that is perpendicular to the three-dimensional cubic space, and with these, there forms a five-dimensional space, as is presented also in Sefer Yetzirah. The Y ( &lt;strong&gt;י&lt;/strong&gt; ) is, as noted, a point of contact for additional dimension(s), especially by means of its top tip, that represents the trend towards innumerable dimensions, or a point of contact with still higher worlds. While this geometrical understanding is based on the form of the Hebrew letters in the square (&lt;em&gt;Ashuri&lt;/em&gt;) script, it is also valid to the round cursive form of the Hebrew letters. The letter H of these round letters represents a circle (or a ring between concentric circles). In this way, the tower would be in a form of a cylinder, whose top is surrounded by a Dome that represents the two higher hyper-dimensions. Intriguingly – this geometric scheme of “The Name of the Lord” is realized in the very ceiling of the Dome of the Rock on Jerusalem Temple Mount - 32 figures with 32 “paths of Wisdom” between them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Yitzhaq Hayut-Man, Ph.D</name></author><summary type="html">https://www.thehope.org/regenesis/appendix-1-b-worlds-multidimensions-of-genesis/</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Appendix 1-C: The New Jerusalem Diagram in the First Verse of Genesis</title><link href="/regenesis/2010/03/12/appendix-1-c-the-new-jerusalem-diagram-in-the-first-verse-of-genesis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Appendix 1-C: The New Jerusalem Diagram in the First Verse of Genesis" /><published>2010-03-12T07:05:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-03-12T07:05:00+02:00</updated><id>/regenesis/2010/03/12/appendix-1-c-the-new-jerusalem-diagram-in-the-first-verse-of-genesis</id><content type="html" xml:base="/regenesis/2010/03/12/appendix-1-c-the-new-jerusalem-diagram-in-the-first-verse-of-genesis.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/diagram.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the-new-jerusalem-diagram-in-the-first-verse-of-genesis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Appendix: The New Jerusalem Diagram (NJD) of ancient Cosmology; First hint of the NJD in the number of letters in the 1st word and 1st verse of Genesis enfold the NJD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Re-GENESIS Project, &lt;strong&gt;Appendix 1-C:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-new-jerusalem-diagram&quot;&gt;The New Jerusalem Diagram&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-the-first-verse-of-genesis&quot;&gt;in the First Verse of Genesis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The New Jerusalem Diagram” is the name given by the earth mysteries researcher John Michell to a diagram that facilitates “squaring the Circle” and its division to 28 equal segments, and the ritual placement of the twelve constellations in the pattern of four camps of three tribes each on the four sides of the circle. Michell claimed that this diagram served the design of many ancient sacred sites, including the Great Pyramid of Gize and Stonehenge in England, and is hinted and enfolded, he claims, in the description of the holy city, The New Jerusalem, whose descent from heaven concludes the Christian Bible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first verse Genesis, made of seven Hebrew words and 28 letters, it says: “ &lt;strong&gt;Bereshit bara Elohim et haShamayim vet haAreẓ&lt;/strong&gt;”. In these words is hinted the secret of geometry (namely of measuring the earth) of heaven and earth. In the ancient world, the skys were considered as circle or dome and the earth as a square or a cube.[&lt;strong&gt;[1]&lt;/strong&gt;] The desired harmony between heaven and earth was conceived as a geometric riddle of harmonizing the circle and the square, as well as between the cube and the dome. The problem with “squaring the circle” is that the square represent “rational” relations between its components (that is, they divide into the ration between whole and finite numbers), whereas the circle represents “irrational” relations (the ratio between its elements, the circumference and the diameter, is infinite) and is expressed by the symbol π. It is therefore impossible to draw a square and a circle that have exactly the same circumference (or area). Yet there is a rational approximation that is good enough for a drawing or a physical construction -  the approximation of 22/7 =\&amp;gt; π. With this approximation, the circumference of a square whose length and its breadth are 22 units (22x4 = 88) equals the circumference of a circle whose diameter (d) is 28 units (d π = 28 X 22/7 = 88. What is striking is that these numbers – 28, 7 and 22 – are hinted and enfolded in the first verse of Genesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The construction of this diagram starts with the attempt to “square the circle” by drawing a circle and a square that have the same circumference. So in building this sacred diagram, one starts with a circle with a diameter of 22 units, and blocks it with a square of 22x22 units (like the number of the Hebrew letters, with which supposedly “heaven and earth were made”). Then one draws from the same centre an additional circle whose diameter is 28 units – “the perfect number” that is already the number of the letters in the first verse of genesis and marks the circle of the seasons. The circle with diameter 28 has circumference of π x  28, which is as noted 22/7 x 28 = 88 – just the circumference of the square with edges of 22 and circumference thus 2 x 22 = 88. The circle and the square have the same circumference, and they intersect in 8 points, where the square juts out of the circle in 4 vertices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The building of the complete pattern continues with the drawing of 12 circles with diameter of 6 units – the number of letters in the first word of Genesis – &lt;em&gt;Bereshit&lt;/em&gt; – as the first “perfect number”. The centers of these twelve circles are situated on the outer big circle, whose diameter is 28, and they touch (are tangent to) the inner circle, whose diameter is 22. Four of these circles are situated according to the points were the square is tangent to the inner circle, and the other 8 circles are placed according to the 8 points of intersection between the square and the outer circle. There are two amazing consequences of this construction: (a) This construction divides the circle into 28 equal segments; and (b) the ratio of 22;6, which issues theoretical-geometrical considerations is also the exact real ratio between the diameter of the earth and the diameter of the moon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E.g. “Round Sky and Square Earth (&lt;em&gt;Tian Yuan Di Fang&lt;/em&gt;): Ancient Chinese Geographical Thought and its Influence”. http://www.springerlink.com/content/pp4p0287796183m7/.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.global-report.com/thehope/a80-chapter-1-exegesis-for-parashat-bereshit&quot;&gt;To return to Re-GENESIS Chapter 1 (Parashat Bereshit)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.global-report.com/thehope/a94-appendix-3-b-abrahamic-magic-gematria-and-geomancy&quot;&gt;To proceed to The Application of the New Jerusalem Diagram by Abraham&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.global-report.com/thehope/a94-appendix-3-b-abrahamic-magic-gematria-and-geomancy&quot;&gt;http://www.global-report.com/thehope/a94-appendix-3-b-abrahamic-magic-gematria-and-geomancy&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional articles about this diagram:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thehope.org/njframe.htm&quot;&gt;http://www.thehope.org/njframe.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:New_Jerusalem_(Michell)_Sacred_Geometry.svg&quot;&gt;http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:New_Jerusalem_(Michell)_Sacred_Geometry.svg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.constructingtheuniverse.com/Volume5.html&quot;&gt;http://www.constructingtheuniverse.com/Volume5.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thesecretofom.com/njmandala.html&quot;&gt;http://www.thesecretofom.com/njmandala.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two articles about the Diagram on this site have been copied to a book-size page with many more resources, at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.world-mysteries.com/science/the-new-jerusalem-diagram/&quot;&gt;http://blog.world-mysteries.com/science/the-new-jerusalem-diagram/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Article viewed  &lt;strong&gt;8095&lt;/strong&gt;  times&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Yitzhaq Hayut-Man, Ph.D</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Appendix 1-D: The Servant Nation in the Haphtarah of Genesis</title><link href="/blog/2010/03/12/appendix-1-d-the-servant-nation-in-the-haphtarah-of-genesis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Appendix 1-D: The Servant Nation in the Haphtarah of Genesis" /><published>2010-03-12T07:05:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-03-12T07:05:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/2010/03/12/appendix-1-d-the-servant-nation-in-the-haphtarah-of-genesis</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2010/03/12/appendix-1-d-the-servant-nation-in-the-haphtarah-of-genesis.html">&lt;p&gt;the-servant-nation-in-the-haphtarah-of-genesis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-servant-nation-in-the-haphtarah-of-genesis&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Servant Nation in the Haphtarah of Genesis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yitzhaq Hayut-Man&lt;/strong&gt; _ 14.10.2012 07:10_&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;www.thehope.org/r-the-servant-nation-in-the-haphtarah-of-genesis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How the Servant Nation idea is already connected to the Creation narrative through Haphtarah of Isaiah 42-43.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Servant Nation in the **&lt;/strong&gt; Haphtarah &lt;strong&gt;** of Genesis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already written about the Torah being actually &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.global-report.com/thehope/a78-re-genesis-now-project-preface-introduction&quot;&gt;written in future tense&lt;/a&gt;, rather than a past history - and thus forming a prophecy for our time, and also written about the apparent three stories of Creation as corresponding to the three distinct levels of Being –  &lt;strong&gt;Beri'ah, Yeẓirah&lt;/strong&gt;  and  &lt;strong&gt;Ạssiyah&lt;/strong&gt;. There are also appendices about the Tree of Life Pattern, the Multidimensional structure of Genesis and about the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.global-report.com/thehope/a83-1-c-the-new-jerusalem-diagram-in-the-first-verse-of-genesis&quot;&gt;New Jerusalem Diagram&lt;/a&gt; embedded within the first verse of Genesis. Having raised the cause of the Universal New Israel as the global “Servant Nation”, we can check how the ideas of the Servant Nation and the Messiah connect with the first Portion of &lt;em&gt;Bereshit&lt;/em&gt;/Genesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is indeed a &lt;em&gt;Midrash&lt;/em&gt; that claims that the “Spirit of (or Wind from) God hovering over the (sur)face of the waters” (Gen 1:2, literal translation, respecting the original tense) is 'the Spirit of the Messiah' (&lt;em&gt;Bereshit Raba&lt;/em&gt;, 2:4).1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main connection is through the  **Haphtarah - ** the Jewish ritual of reading sections from the writings of the prophets on Sabbaths and festivals after the reading from the Torah. The &lt;em&gt;Haphtarah _text&lt;/em&gt; _is brought to amplify a certain point in the text of the Torah portion, a point that is explicit or implicit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the occasion of the first reading of Bereshit (Genesis) cycle, the &lt;em&gt;Haphtarah&lt;/em&gt; section is from Isaiah, from 42:5 to 43:10 – which is largely about “The Servant of YHWH” – a concept that caused many debates between Jews and Christians over the centuries, debating whether this is an individual or the entire Nation of Israel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of “The Servant of YHWH” already appears in the former chapter of Isaiah (“Second Isaiah” according to most Bible scholars) – “But thou, Yisra'el, art my servant, Ya'ạqov (Jacob) whom I have chosen” (Isaiah 41:8). So this is the entire nation as the Servant. But in chapter 42, just before the Haphtarah, there are four verses that describe this servant in more personal terms. The first of them says: “Behold My servant, whom I uphold; My elect, in whom my soul delights; I have put my spirit upon him; he shall bring forth judgment to the nations” (Is. 42:1). It could even be argued that the Haphtarah does not begin with the beginning of the chapter because the Jewish sages who selected the Haphtarah wanted to avoid this embarrassment.2 &lt;a href=&quot;../../C:%5C%5CUsers%5C%5CUser%5C%5CDownloads%5C%5CServant%20Nation%20of%20Genesis.docx#_ftn2&quot;&gt;[2](../../C:%5C%5CUsers%5C%5CUser%5C%5CDownloads%5C%5CServant%20Nation%20of%20Genesis.docx#_ftn2)[]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the more likely reason the Haftarah starts on verse 5 is that here comes the Acts of Creation: “Thus says God the Lord (&lt;em&gt;haEl YHWH&lt;/em&gt;), He that created the heavens, and stretched them out; He that spread forth the earth, and that which comes out of it; He that gives breath (also Divine Soul - &lt;strong&gt;Neshamah&lt;/strong&gt; ) to the nation ( &lt;strong&gt;Ạm&lt;/strong&gt; ) upon it, and Spirit ( &lt;strong&gt;Ru'aḥ&lt;/strong&gt; ) to them that walk therein” (Isaiah 42:5). This parallels the first verse of Genesis, only here there are four actions: heaven and earth – as in the Genesis account – but also giving of the Divine Soul ( &lt;strong&gt;Neshamah&lt;/strong&gt; ) to the nation ( &lt;strong&gt;ha'Ạm&lt;/strong&gt; ) and Spirit to the people at large. The next verse repeats the notion of the nation and expands upon it: “I the Lord (&lt;em&gt;YHWH&lt;/em&gt;) have called thee in righteousness, and will hold thy hand, and will keep thee, and give thee as a covenant of a nation ( &lt;strong&gt;Brit Ạm&lt;/strong&gt; ), for a light of the nations” ( &lt;strong&gt;Or Goyim&lt;/strong&gt; ).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Genesis account, God creates light as the first creation. Here Israel is conceived as “A Light for/of the Nations”. The notion of light then repeats several times in the portion, along the notion of blindness and overcoming blindness by giving light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us look at the main themes of this passage by counting key words. The Name of the Lord (&lt;em&gt;YHWH&lt;/em&gt;) appears 13 times, and He declares Himself as “Ani” (I Am) 6 times. The last time it comes as “ &lt;strong&gt;Ani Hu&lt;/strong&gt; _” _– “I am He” (who creates and does all the marvels listed before). Blindness is mentioned 7 times, of which three times that the Servant of God (identified once as “ &lt;strong&gt;Meshulam&lt;/strong&gt;”, literally “perfected” or “paid for”) is himself blind – “Hear, O deaf; and look, O blind, that you may see. Who is blind, but My servant? Or deaf as My messenger that I sent? Who is blind as he that is perfected and blind as the Lord's servant” – and four times are about opening blind eyes. Against these there are seven mentions of seeing and of light, starting with the Servant Nation of the Lord being “Light of the Nations”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These mentions of light, seeing and comprehending are again connected to the Genesis narrative. Recall that the first command or act is “Let there be light” (Gen. 1:2-5). Thus, the Servant Nation of Israel emulates God's creation and is in fact a co-creator.3 This leads to the &lt;em&gt;Midrash&lt;/em&gt; on the word “ &lt;strong&gt;Bereshit&lt;/strong&gt;” (at the beginning) – that the world was created “for the sake of Israel who are called “ &lt;strong&gt;Reshit&lt;/strong&gt;” (&lt;em&gt;vayiqra Raba&lt;/em&gt; 36:4, based on Jer. 2:3). This may seem to any non-Israelite as sheer impudence. But to put it in perspective, the Midrash says that “each and every person (Adam, not necessarily Israelite) ought to say 'the world was created for my sake” (&lt;em&gt;Mishna Sanhedrin&lt;/em&gt; 4:5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also still another implicit connection between the first portion of Genesis and this section from Isaiah. We noted earlier that there are three creation stories one after the other: (1) about the Creation of Heaven and Earth (Gen. 1:1), (2) about the “generations” or products ( &lt;strong&gt;Toldot&lt;/strong&gt; ) of the Heaven and Earth (Gen 2:4) and (3) about the generations/products of Adam (Mankind) starting on Genesis 5:1. We claim that these correspond to the levels of Being: Creation ( &lt;strong&gt;Bri'ah&lt;/strong&gt; ) &lt;strong&gt;, ** Formation ( **Yeẓirah&lt;/strong&gt; ), and of Making ( &lt;strong&gt;Ạssiyah&lt;/strong&gt; ). These three terms are mentioned explicitly in the passage in Isaiah: “Every one that is called by My Name, for I have created him ( &lt;strong&gt;bra'ativ&lt;/strong&gt; ) for My glory, I have formed him ( &lt;strong&gt;yeẓartiv&lt;/strong&gt; ); yea, I have made him ( &lt;strong&gt;ạssitiv&lt;/strong&gt;”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Article viewed  &lt;strong&gt;2019&lt;/strong&gt;  times in the older website&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ap2-a-the-names-of-noaḥ-and-his-sons&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ap.2-A: The NAMES of NOAḤ And His SONS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Yitzḥaq Ḥayut-Man&lt;/strong&gt; _ 12.04.2010_&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;http://www.thehope/regenesis/2-A_the_names_of_noaḥ_and_his_sons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix: The Hidden Wisdom encoded in the names of Noah and his progeny - A Sample Lesson for a future “Academy of Shem and Ẹver”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Re-GENESIS NOW Project &lt;strong&gt;Chapter 2, Appendix 2-A&lt;/strong&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-names-of-noaḥ-and-his-sons&quot;&gt;The Names of Noaḥ and his Sons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contents:
The name “ &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;” ( &lt;strong&gt;נח&lt;/strong&gt; ) and  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;ח”ן&lt;/strong&gt; ) - “the Hidden Knowledge”
&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  and Consolation (Neḥamah)
&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  -  &lt;strong&gt;Guidance&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;nḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ),  &lt;strong&gt;Camping&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ) and  &lt;strong&gt;Rest&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;nuḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; )
&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  -  &lt;strong&gt;Laying&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ) and  &lt;strong&gt;Landing&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;ḥit&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; )
&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  and  &lt;strong&gt;Sacrificial Offering ** ( **M&lt;/strong&gt; i &lt;strong&gt;nḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; )
From  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  to  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;mi&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; ,  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  and  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;nin&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;
The  &lt;strong&gt;Name&lt;/strong&gt;  of  &lt;strong&gt;No&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;נוח&lt;/strong&gt;  - with full spelling) and the number 64
The  &lt;strong&gt;Name&lt;/strong&gt;  “ &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;”
The  &lt;strong&gt;Academies of S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;  and  &lt;strong&gt;Ẹ&lt;/strong&gt; ve &lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The name **” **N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;” ( &lt;strong&gt;נח&lt;/strong&gt; ) and  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  The sentence “and  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; ( &lt;strong&gt;ח”ן&lt;/strong&gt; ) - “ &lt;strong&gt;the Hidden Knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen that in the name “ &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;” ( &lt;strong&gt;נח&lt;/strong&gt; ) there is a hint about  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;ח”ן&lt;/strong&gt; ) - “the Hidden Knowledge” (&lt;em&gt;Ḥokhmat haNistar&lt;/em&gt;) and, indeed, there are many secrets hidden within the name “ &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;” and its Gematria value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many Hassidic texts,  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  is the occult wisdom. For example, in the first teaching of Rabbi Nachman of Breslow's collection (&lt;em&gt;Liqute Moharan&lt;/em&gt;) is that the  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;ח”ן&lt;/strong&gt; ) is the capacity to bring the prayer to be accepted. The letter  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; et ( &lt;strong&gt;ח&lt;/strong&gt; ) signifies vitality ( &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;yut&lt;/strong&gt; ) and Wisdom ( &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;k&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ), the Sun and the Intellect, whereas the letter  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; un ( &lt;strong&gt;נ&lt;/strong&gt; ון) signifies the Sephirah of Malkhut (the Feminine) and the Moon. The secret lies in joining them together through prayer and the study of the inner domain of the Torah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  and  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  have the Gematria value of 58. The number 58 is the sum of the two numbers that we have explored in the first portion, Parashat Bereshit: 32 “wonderous paths of wisdom” (of 4D) and 26 (Gematria of the Name YHWH), which are the number of directions in the (3D) World of Formation – 32 + 26 = 58. The summation 32 + 26 recalls the two words  &lt;strong&gt;Kvod YHWH&lt;/strong&gt; , which is the Divine Glory through which the hidden deity appears in this world, whether through the clouds of glory at the exodus and the Tabernacle, or at the Jerusalem Temple or in the cloud of Ezekiel's vision. The first appearance of the divine glory, however, is in the rainbow of the Covenant with Noah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number 58 has deep connection to the system of “Names of  &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;W&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;Y&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;” that are derived by “filling” with the letters of the names of the four letters of the Name of YHWH. Several alternative fillings are possible, due to the different spellings of the letters  &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;'e ( &lt;strong&gt;ה&lt;/strong&gt; ) and  &lt;strong&gt;W&lt;/strong&gt;'aw &lt;strong&gt;(ו&lt;/strong&gt;) – namely הא, הה, הו and ואו, וו, ויו. The Lurianic Kabbalah employed four such names – Shem ẠB with Gematria value of 72,  &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;G&lt;/strong&gt;  with value of 63,  &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;  with value of 45 and  &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  whose numerical value is 52. Now (72 + 63 + 45 + 52) / 4 = 58, which is the median value of the four Names of  &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;W&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;Y&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now  &lt;strong&gt;58&lt;/strong&gt;    &lt;strong&gt;הי ואו הה יוד&lt;/strong&gt;  (reading from right to left). So 58 is the value of another Name of  &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;W&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;Y&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; , one that is arranged according to the order of the four Names –  &lt;strong&gt;יוד&lt;/strong&gt;  (fitting  &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m ẠB&lt;/strong&gt; , written in the same unchanging manner for all the four Holy Names), ** &lt;strong&gt;** הי&lt;/strong&gt; (fitting &lt;strong&gt;S **&lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; m S &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; G &lt;strong&gt;, written with the letter&lt;/strong&gt; Y'&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;ud&lt;/em&gt; which is used in both Shem ẠB and Shem SaG),  ואו (fitting with **S **&lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; m M &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; H&lt;strong&gt;, written with the letter Aleph (&lt;/strong&gt;א&lt;strong&gt;) of **S **&lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; m H &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; W &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Y &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; H** with the filling of Alephs, where the word “Aleph” means training and instruction), and &lt;strong&gt;הה&lt;/strong&gt; (fitting with &lt;strong&gt;S **&lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; m B &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; N** and written in the form of the automatic reverberation of letters, which is characteristic of this Name). So this hidden Holy Name contains and connects the qualities of the other Holy Names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number 58 is also connected with the first divine creation utterance: the Gematria value of “ &lt;strong&gt;Y&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; ** Or&lt;strong&gt;” ( **יהי אור&lt;/strong&gt;  - let there be light) is 232, that is, 58 times four (and we have already shown that 4 is connected with building).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name “ &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;” itself is a word (or  &lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;v&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;  – “box”) of two letters. The original Hebrew word roots are of two letters (as in the grammar of the Sefer Yeẓirah). The roots that are employed nowadays are of three letters, and the two-letter combination “Noaḥ” comprises a part of several Hebrew word roots with their various manifestations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(note: in the following examples, the Biblical quotations are given in purple and the letters of the name of &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; are marked in red, e.g. ) &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; ; the Hebrew root letters in a transliterated Hebrew word and name are marked as &lt;strong&gt;bold,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  and  &lt;strong&gt;Consolation&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And he (Lemekh) called his name Noaḥ, saying, This one shall comfort us ( &lt;strong&gt;ye&lt;/strong&gt;** n &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; m &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; nu&lt;strong&gt;) for our work and the toil of our hands, because of the ground (&lt;em&gt;Adamah&lt;/em&gt; – living earth) which the Lord has cursed” (Gen. 5:29). On the other hand: “And the Lord (YHWH) repented (&lt;/strong&gt;v &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; y &lt;strong&gt;i&lt;/strong&gt; n &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;e&lt;/strong&gt; m&lt;strong&gt;) that he had made man on earth, and it grieved him at his heart. And the Lord said, I will destroy man (Adam) whom I have created from the face of the earth (Adamah): both man (Adam) and beast (Behemah), and creeping things, and the birds of the air; for I repent (&lt;/strong&gt;n &lt;strong&gt;i&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; mti&lt;strong&gt;)  that I have made them. But **N **oa&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ** found favour (&lt;strong&gt;Ḥ **e&lt;/strong&gt; n**) in the eyes of the Lord” (6:6-8).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both passages there is an association of the name “ &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;” with “ &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;”, but in two different senses, positive and negative. There is a  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;  of restoration, and there is  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;  of regret and desire to annul that which has been made. Perhaps because of the good hope that his father expected from him, that his son would become the comforter of humankind, that Noaḥ became “a just man and perfect”, and when “all flesh had corrupted its way” still “Noaḥ found favour ( &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; ) in the eyes of the Lord”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  -  &lt;strong&gt;Guidance&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;nḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ),  &lt;strong&gt;Camping&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ),  &lt;strong&gt;Res&lt;/strong&gt; t ( &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;** u &lt;strong&gt;**ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Parashah of  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  tells about the dove that was sent after the raven, and at first “the dove found no rest (Menuḥah) for the sole of her foot, and she returned to him into the ark” (8:9).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And it came to pass, when Par'ọh had let the people go, that God led them ( &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; ) not through the way of the land of the &lt;em&gt;Pelishtim,&lt;/em&gt; although that was near; for God said, Lest the people regret ( &lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; ) when they see war, and they return to Miẓrayim”(Exodus 13:17). The motif of guidance repeats at the same chapter (verse 21): “And the Lord went before them by day in a pillar of a cloud, to lead them ( &lt;strong&gt;l&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;nḥ&lt;/strong&gt;** ot &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; m&lt;strong&gt;) the way; and by night in a pillar of fire to give them light, that they might go by day and night”. The order of the journeys was “they departe/removed from X…. and they pitched (&lt;/strong&gt;v &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; y &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; n&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;u&lt;/em&gt;) at Y”: guidance - **h **&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; nḥ &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; y &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; h** - (through the lillar of smoke and of fire) and then camping - &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ **a&lt;/strong&gt; n &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; y &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; h&lt;strong&gt;. (And we learn that the inspiration of the Torah to Moshe occurred only when the children of Israel campted (&lt;/strong&gt;ḥ &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; n &lt;strong&gt;**u&lt;/strong&gt; ) and found rest ( &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;** u &lt;strong&gt;**ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ). Only then the Levites erected the Tabernacle and Moshe could enter to the innermost chamber to the dwelling (Shekhinah) of God and then hear “the voice speaking to him from off the covering that was upon the ark of testimony, from between the two keruvim: and it spke to him” (Numbers 7:89).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\&amp;lt;\&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;**  - Laying&lt;strong&gt;(&lt;/strong&gt;h &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; n &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; h&lt;strong&gt;) and&lt;/strong&gt; Landing&lt;strong&gt;(&lt;/strong&gt;n &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;**it&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is written about Adam “And the Lord God (YHWH Elohim) took the man (adam), and put him (vayaniḥehu) into the garden of Ẹden” (Gen. 2:15) - he was put by God inside the perfect environment that has been previously been prepared for him, though for the need “to till it and to keep it”. Noa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  too was put, as if laid, into the special environment – but this time it was an artificial ecological environment. an “Ecosystem”, that had been built by Noah and his sons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  was also the first man to land ( &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;** a &lt;strong&gt;**ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;** a &lt;strong&gt;**t&lt;/strong&gt; ) from his vessel to the renewed (“terraformed”) earth. Landing is a sort of descent and fall, and we shall see the landing down of  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;  in the drunkenness and the inferiority ( &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; i &lt;strong&gt;tut&lt;/strong&gt; ) of  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;**   &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt;  Sacrificial Offering&lt;strong&gt;(&lt;/strong&gt;M &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; nḥ &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; h**)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon exiting the Ark,  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  made another building operation: “and  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  built an altar to the Lord; and took of every clean beast, and of every clean bird, and offered burnt offerings on the altar” (8:20).  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  appears here as a priest who brings sacrifices, and one (in contradistinction to Qayin) whose sacrifice was accepted. From here on the issue of sacrifices and offerings will reappear hundreds of times in the Torah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From **&lt;/strong&gt; N &lt;strong&gt;oa&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;** to **&lt;/strong&gt; N &lt;strong&gt;e&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;e&lt;/strong&gt; mi &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; h**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole passage of the Torah and the Prophets goes between these two builders - from the building of the Ark by  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  and his sons to the collective building of the walls of Jerusalem under the direction of  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;mi&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;. Inside the box of the walls of Jerusalem the Temple was rebuilt as the place of safeguarding and editing of the Torah through  &lt;strong&gt;Ẹzra&lt;/strong&gt;  the scribe and his entourage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In between we find  &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;** o &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;, the father of Samson, who is the prototype of the victorious Messiah. As for the name of the last Messiah, there are many conjectures, but the most common is that his name would be ** M **e&lt;/strong&gt; n &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;e&lt;/strong&gt; m** (comforter).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; ,  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  and  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;** in &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; h**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After God repented ( &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; i &lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt;** n &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;e&lt;/strong&gt; m&lt;strong&gt;) that He has created humankind and decided to destroy them, he had mercy (&lt;/strong&gt;ḥ &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; n &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; n&lt;strong&gt;) toward Noaḥ - the one who “found grace (&lt;/strong&gt;Ḥ &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; n&lt;strong&gt;) in the eyes of the Lord” (Gen. 6:8). The virtue of Noah brought out the divine qualities of being merciful (&lt;/strong&gt;ḥ &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; n &lt;strong&gt;**un&lt;/strong&gt; ) and compassionate ( &lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;** um**).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sentence “and  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;oa&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  found  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;” is an obvious and intended word play. “ &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;” is “ &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;” spelled backward. The word “ &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;” is commonly explained as the acronym of “ &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;k&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; _ _ &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;st&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt;” (Hidden Wisdom) or &lt;strong&gt;ח&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;“&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ן&lt;/strong&gt; (and there are also those explaining it as “ &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;k&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt; _ _ &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;s&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;im&lt;/strong&gt;” (Feminine Wisdom).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted in the chapter, the Gematria value of  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  (who is “husbandman of the Adamah”, the living Earth; Gen. 9:20) is 58, which is also the Gematria value of “ &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;G&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;” – the known garden, the Garden of  &lt;strong&gt;Ẹd&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Name Noaḥ ** ( **נוח ** - with full spelling) and  **the number 64&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, the name is generally spelled in its full form as  &lt;strong&gt;No&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  -  &lt;strong&gt;נוח&lt;/strong&gt;. This name (in its full spelling, with the addition of the letter W'aw (ו), which is one of the letters of the Name of YHWH) has the Gematria value of 64 (the full number of situations in the Chinese I-Ching or “Book of Changes”; whereas in the Qabbalah by Gematria S'D ( &lt;strong&gt;ס&lt;/strong&gt;” &lt;strong&gt;ד&lt;/strong&gt; ) – the common acronym of “ &lt;strong&gt;Siạt&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h d&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;” (Divine Help). This Gematria value is equal to that of “ &lt;strong&gt;Ad&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;  ve &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;v&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;” (Adam and Eve) – with Noah there is a new beginning to humankind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We find the word spelled this way only once in the Torah: “And the Lord came down in a cloud, and spoke to him, and took of the spirit that emenated upon him, and gave it to the seventy elders; and it came to pass that when the spirit rested upon them ( &lt;strong&gt;k&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;'&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;** o &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ** &lt;em&gt;ạleyhem haruaḥ),&lt;/em&gt; they prophesied, but continued not” (Numbers 11:25).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spirit that emanated upon Moshe also alighted ( &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ) upon the seventy elders of Israel. Likewise, “And when the sons of the prophets who were in  &lt;strong&gt;Y&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;riḥo&lt;/strong&gt;  (Jericho) saw him, they said, The spirit of Eliyahu (Elijah) rests ( &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ) on Elisha; And they came to meet him, and bowed themselves to the grouond before him” (II Kings 2:15). And similarly: “And there shall come forth a rod of the stem of Yishay, and a branch shall grow out of his roots; and the spirit of the Lord shall rest ( &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ) upon him, the spirit of wisdom and understanding, the spirit of counsel and might, the spirit of knowledge and of the fear of the Lord” (Isaiah 11:1). There is a passage of the spirit of prophecy through a stage of “ &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;”, of rest ( &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;** u &lt;strong&gt;**ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ) and passivity.4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name, or the principle, of “ &lt;strong&gt;No&lt;/strong&gt;'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;” ( &lt;strong&gt;נוח&lt;/strong&gt; ) is as result from the entry of the penetration of the W'aw of the holy spirit into the passive state of  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number 64 is a significant number in its own right: 64 = 2^6 = 4^3 = 8^2, namely the number of square cells in a flat square of 8, like a chess board; the number of cubical cells in a box of 4x4x4 (and also the number of 6D cells of a 6D hypercube of 2x2x2x2x2x2). 64 is the number of world-year-soul states which are at the basis of the Taoist world-view and the I-Ching book, where they are represented by the 64 hexagrams. These 64 states are generally presented on the plane, in the form of 8x8, but these 64 states can also be arrayed in a cube of 4x4x4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number 64 has connection to the fourth “perfect Number (apparently the largest perfect number known in antiquity), which is 8128: 127 x 64 = 8,128. So, this perfect number is the product of the spatial principle of 64 and of another principle expressed by the number 127. We shall meet this number later, in the Parasha of  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ye&lt;/strong&gt; _ _ &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; , where we shall be able to appreciate the appearance of the fourth perfect number related to the cave of  &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;k&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;pel&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;  (multiplication) in &lt;strong&gt;Qiryat Arbạ&lt;/strong&gt; (City of the Four).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The  &lt;strong&gt;Name&lt;/strong&gt;  “ &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  is the “second round” of Adam. In the first deed of Adam, he composed names (Shemot) to all the animals, whereas the first creation of  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; , his firstborn, he called “ &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;”, namely “Name”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name “ &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;” is a root to the letters of  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;s&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;ha&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;נשמה&lt;/strong&gt; ) – the Eternal or Over Soul. It is there between the letters  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; un ( &lt;strong&gt;נ&lt;/strong&gt;  or ** ן** ) - that signifies the Sephirah of  &lt;strong&gt;Bin&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; (“the 50 {' &lt;strong&gt;נ&lt;/strong&gt; } Gates of  &lt;strong&gt;Bin&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;” {Understanding}; and the lower  &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;'e { &lt;strong&gt;ה&lt;/strong&gt; } of the name of  &lt;strong&gt;YHWH&lt;/strong&gt; , representing the Shekhinah and the World of Action. The connection between  &lt;strong&gt;Bin&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;” {Understanding} and Action is through The Name -  &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; ), which means that to comprehend and understand the components and procedures of action, one needs to give them names that explain them and that combine to a full explanation, (the Higher Knowledge - &lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a'&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ạt Ẹlyon&lt;/strong&gt; ).5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest value of contemporary Judaism is “ &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;” ( &lt;strong&gt;השם&lt;/strong&gt; ), which is the reverse order of the letters of the name “ &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; o &lt;strong&gt;s&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;” (Moses –  &lt;strong&gt;משה&lt;/strong&gt; ). In the Torah of Moshe, the divine name is of  &lt;strong&gt;YHWH&lt;/strong&gt;. Present day Jews do not dare to pronounce the explicit Name and call it “ &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;” (meaning literally “The Name”).  It is said (in Naḥmanides' (&lt;em&gt;Ramban&lt;/em&gt;) Torah commentary and in the Book of Zohar) that the whole entire Torah is the expanded Great Name of the Holy One. Therefore, also whoever reads aloud the Torah (&lt;em&gt;qore baTorah&lt;/em&gt;) in truth, for its own sake (&lt;em&gt;Torah lishmah&lt;/em&gt;) – (s)he is calling the divinity in her full name (&lt;em&gt;Shem haMeforash&lt;/em&gt;) and may receive the answer of the Holy One.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let us look at the significance coded in the sum of the Gematria values of Noah and his sons: No'aḥ  58 + Shem  340 + Ḥam  48 + Yefet  490 = 936. The number 936, in turn 936 = 26 x 36. As we've already seen, 26 signifies the Name of  &lt;strong&gt;YHWH&lt;/strong&gt; , whereas 36 signifies the array of “ &lt;strong&gt;El&lt;/strong&gt; eh” ( &lt;strong&gt;אלה&lt;/strong&gt; ) – the manifest parts of God ( &lt;strong&gt;El&lt;/strong&gt; o &lt;strong&gt;him&lt;/strong&gt; ).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Academies of Shem and Ẹver&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The midrashim6tell of Noah's descendants  &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;  and  &lt;strong&gt;Ẹv&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt;  as if they held an academy (&lt;em&gt;Beit Midrash&lt;/em&gt;) where they taught the  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  – the hidden wisdom of the Sons of Noah, especially the secrets of the Hebrew names –  &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;mot&lt;/strong&gt; _ _ &lt;strong&gt;Ịvr&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;yim&lt;/strong&gt;  – and the Hebrew letters –  &lt;strong&gt;Ot&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;yot&lt;/strong&gt; _ _ &lt;strong&gt;Ịvr&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;io&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;yot&lt;/strong&gt;. This amounts to a  &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;** i&lt;strong&gt;-Semantic study place (&lt;em&gt;Beit Midrash&lt;/em&gt;) that uses a universal language, assembled from all the world's languages and finds parallels among the diverse names, which is also a Hebrew exegesis – **M **&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; dr &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; s &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;h _** Ịv ****r**** i ** - that is based on Hebrew Language - ** Ịvr **_i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; t**_ _– as a universal esoteric language and searches to find the secrets that issue from the Hebrew letters, words and names. This operation may lead to the realization of the prophecy of Ẓephanyah “For then I will convert the people to a purer language”. This will be the rectification to the confusion of languages of Babel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By Gematria, “ &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;” + “ &lt;strong&gt;Ẹv&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt;”  340 + 272 = 612 (as the 613 commands minus one), which is also the Gematria value of  &lt;strong&gt;Brit&lt;/strong&gt;  – covenant. To the extent that the Noahide dispensation may get accepted in the world, the pupils of the future academy of Shem and Ẹver would likely be allies to Israel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entire appendix may conceivably be regarded as a sample lesson of a modern incarnation of the Academy of Shem and Ẹver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have started this article noting Rabbi &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;ḥm&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; (Nachman) of Breslow's claim that the letters of  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;ח”ן&lt;/strong&gt; ) have the capacity to bring the prayer to be accepted. We may end by pointing to the phenomenon of his adherents writing the name “Noaḥ” as graffiti on walls all over Israel as a sign of the Times:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;                 **N** a -  **N** a **ḥ**  -  **N** a **ḥ**** m ** - ** N **a** ḥ ****m** a **n**  -  **N** a **ḥ**** m **a** n ** ** m **&amp;amp;#39;** Um **a** n**
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{Article viewed  &lt;strong&gt;4875&lt;/strong&gt;  times between 12.04.2010 and 1.1.19}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes:
[1] Already the Sages observed the special character of the letters  &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;'e and  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;'un, in that they are “letters that have no coupling (Zivug)” (whereas Aleph + Tet = Bet + Ḥet = Gimmel + Zayin = 10, and likewise with the letters Y'ud till Ẓadi). Therefore, their coupling is with “the aid of the Name (&lt;em&gt;be'ẹzrat haShem&lt;/em&gt;)”, which connects them to form “ &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;s&lt;/strong&gt; ha &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;” ( &lt;strong&gt;נשמה&lt;/strong&gt; )” - oversoul.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">the-servant-nation-in-the-haphtarah-of-genesis</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Appendix 2-A: The Names of Noaḥ And His Sons</title><link href="/blog/2010/03/12/appendix-2-a-the-names-of-noah-and-his-sons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Appendix 2-A: The Names of Noaḥ And His Sons" /><published>2010-03-12T07:05:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-03-12T07:05:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/2010/03/12/appendix-2-a-the-names-of-noah-and-his-sons</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2010/03/12/appendix-2-a-the-names-of-noah-and-his-sons.html">&lt;p&gt;the-names-of-noah-and-his-sons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ap2-a-the-names-of-noaḥ-and-his-sons&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ap.2-A: The Names of Noaḥ And His Sons&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Yitzḥaq Ḥayut-Man&lt;/strong&gt; _ 12.04.2010_&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appendix: The Hidden Wisdom encoded in the names of Noah and his progeny - A Sample Lesson for a future &quot;Academy of Shem and Ẹver&quot;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Re-GENESIS NOW Project &lt;strong&gt;Chapter 2, Appendix 2-A&lt;/strong&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-names-of-noaḥ-and-his-sons&quot;&gt;The Names of Noaḥ and his Sons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contents:
The name &quot; &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; ( &lt;strong&gt;נח&lt;/strong&gt; ) and  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;ח&quot;ן&lt;/strong&gt; ) - &quot;the Hidden Knowledge&quot;
&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  and Consolation (Neḥamah)
&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  -  &lt;strong&gt;Guidance&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;nḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ),  &lt;strong&gt;Camping&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ) and  &lt;strong&gt;Rest&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;nuḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; )
&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  -  &lt;strong&gt;Laying&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ) and  &lt;strong&gt;Landing&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;ḥit&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; )
&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  and  &lt;strong&gt;Sacrificial Offering ** ( **M&lt;/strong&gt; i &lt;strong&gt;nḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; )
From  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  to  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;mi&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; ,  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  and  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;nin&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;
The  &lt;strong&gt;Name&lt;/strong&gt;  of  &lt;strong&gt;No&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;נוח&lt;/strong&gt;  - with full spelling) and the number 64
The  &lt;strong&gt;Name&lt;/strong&gt;  &quot; &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;&quot;
The  &lt;strong&gt;Academies of S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;  and  &lt;strong&gt;Ẹ&lt;/strong&gt; ve &lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The name **&quot; **N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; ( &lt;strong&gt;נח&lt;/strong&gt; ) and  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  The sentence &quot;and  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;   ( &lt;strong&gt;ח&quot;ן&lt;/strong&gt; ) - &quot; &lt;strong&gt;the Hidden Knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen that in the name &quot; &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; ( &lt;strong&gt;נח&lt;/strong&gt; ) there is a hint about  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;ח&quot;ן&lt;/strong&gt; ) - &quot;the Hidden Knowledge&quot; (&lt;em&gt;Ḥokhmat haNistar&lt;/em&gt;) and, indeed, there are many secrets hidden within the name &quot; &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; and its Gematria value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many Hassidic texts,  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  is the occult wisdom. For example, in the first teaching of Rabbi Nachman of Breslow's collection (&lt;em&gt;Liqute Moharan&lt;/em&gt;) is that the  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;ח&quot;ן&lt;/strong&gt; ) is the capacity to bring the prayer to be accepted. The letter  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; et ( &lt;strong&gt;ח&lt;/strong&gt; ) signifies vitality ( &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;yut&lt;/strong&gt; ) and Wisdom ( &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;k&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ), the Sun and the Intellect, whereas the letter  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; un ( &lt;strong&gt;נ&lt;/strong&gt; ון) signifies the Sephirah of Malkhut (the Feminine) and the Moon. The secret lies in joining them together through prayer and the study of the inner domain of the Torah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  and  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  have the Gematria value of 58. The number 58 is the sum of the two numbers that we have explored in the first portion, Parashat Bereshit: 32 &quot;wonderous paths of wisdom&quot; (of 4D) and 26 (Gematria of the Name YHWH), which are the number of directions in the (3D) World of Formation – 32 + 26 = 58. The summation 32 + 26 recalls the two words  &lt;strong&gt;Kvod YHWH&lt;/strong&gt; , which is the Divine Glory through which the hidden deity appears in this world, whether through the clouds of glory at the exodus and the Tabernacle, or at the Jerusalem Temple or in the cloud of Ezekiel's vision. The first appearance of the divine glory, however, is in the rainbow of the Covenant with Noah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number 58 has deep connection to the system of &quot;Names of  &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;W&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;Y&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; that are derived by &quot;filling&quot; with the letters of the names of the four letters of the Name of YHWH. Several alternative fillings are possible, due to the different spellings of the letters  &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;'e ( &lt;strong&gt;ה&lt;/strong&gt; ) and  &lt;strong&gt;W&lt;/strong&gt;'aw &lt;strong&gt;(ו&lt;/strong&gt;) – namely הא, הה, הו and ואו, וו, ויו. The Lurianic Kabbalah employed four such names – Shem ẠB with Gematria value of 72,  &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;G&lt;/strong&gt;  with value of 63,  &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;  with value of 45 and  &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  whose numerical value is 52. Now (72 + 63 + 45 + 52) / 4 = 58, which is the median value of the four Names of  &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;W&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;Y&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now  &lt;strong&gt;58&lt;/strong&gt;    &lt;strong&gt;הי ואו הה יוד&lt;/strong&gt;  (reading from right to left). So 58 is the value of another Name of  &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;W&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;Y&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; , one that is arranged according to the order of the four Names –  &lt;strong&gt;יוד&lt;/strong&gt;  (fitting  &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m ẠB&lt;/strong&gt; , written in the same unchanging manner for all the four Holy Names), ** &lt;strong&gt;** הי&lt;/strong&gt; (fitting &lt;strong&gt;S **&lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; m S &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; G &lt;strong&gt;, written with the letter&lt;/strong&gt; Y'&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;ud&lt;/em&gt; which is used in both Shem ẠB and Shem SaG),  ואו (fitting with **S **&lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; m M &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; H&lt;strong&gt;, written with the letter Aleph (&lt;/strong&gt;א&lt;strong&gt;) of **S **&lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; m H &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; W &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Y &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; H** with the filling of Alephs, where the word &quot;Aleph&quot; means training and instruction), and &lt;strong&gt;הה&lt;/strong&gt; (fitting with &lt;strong&gt;S **&lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; m B &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; N** and written in the form of the automatic reverberation of letters, which is characteristic of this Name). So this hidden Holy Name contains and connects the qualities of the other Holy Names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number 58 is also connected with the first divine creation utterance: the Gematria value of &quot; &lt;strong&gt;Y&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; ** Or&lt;strong&gt;&quot; ( **יהי אור&lt;/strong&gt;  - let there be light) is 232, that is, 58 times four (and we have already shown that 4 is connected with building).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name &quot; &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; itself is a word (or  &lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;v&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;  – &quot;box&quot;) of two letters. The original Hebrew word roots are of two letters (as in the grammar of the Sefer Yeẓirah). The roots that are employed nowadays are of three letters, and the two-letter combination &quot;Noaḥ&quot; comprises a part of several Hebrew word roots with their various manifestations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(note: in the following examples, the Biblical quotations are given in purple and the letters of the name of &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; are marked in red, e.g. ) &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; ; the Hebrew root letters in a transliterated Hebrew word and name are marked as &lt;strong&gt;bold,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  and  &lt;strong&gt;Consolation&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;And he (Lemekh) called his name Noaḥ, saying, This one shall comfort us ( &lt;strong&gt;ye&lt;/strong&gt;** n &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; m &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; nu&lt;strong&gt;) for our work and the toil of our hands, because of the ground (&lt;em&gt;Adamah&lt;/em&gt; – living earth) which the Lord has cursed&quot; (Gen. 5:29). On the other hand: &quot;And the Lord (YHWH) repented (&lt;/strong&gt;v &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; y &lt;strong&gt;i&lt;/strong&gt; n &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;e&lt;/strong&gt; m&lt;strong&gt;) that he had made man on earth, and it grieved him at his heart. And the Lord said, I will destroy man (Adam) whom I have created from the face of the earth (Adamah): both man (Adam) and beast (Behemah), and creeping things, and the birds of the air; for I repent (&lt;/strong&gt;n &lt;strong&gt;i&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; mti&lt;strong&gt;)  that I have made them. But **N **oa&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ** found favour (&lt;strong&gt;Ḥ **e&lt;/strong&gt; n**) in the eyes of the Lord&quot; (6:6-8).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both passages there is an association of the name &quot; &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; with &quot; &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;&quot;, but in two different senses, positive and negative. There is a  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;  of restoration, and there is  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;  of regret and desire to annul that which has been made. Perhaps because of the good hope that his father expected from him, that his son would become the comforter of humankind, that Noaḥ became &quot;a just man and perfect&quot;, and when &quot;all flesh had corrupted its way&quot; still &quot;Noaḥ found favour ( &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; ) in the eyes of the Lord&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  -  &lt;strong&gt;Guidance&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;nḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ),  &lt;strong&gt;Camping&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ),  &lt;strong&gt;Res&lt;/strong&gt; t ( &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;** u &lt;strong&gt;**ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Parashah of  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  tells about the dove that was sent after the raven, and at first &quot;the dove found no rest (Menuḥah) for the sole of her foot, and she returned to him into the ark&quot; (8:9).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;And it came to pass, when Par'ọh had let the people go, that God led them ( &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; ) not through the way of the land of the &lt;em&gt;Pelishtim,&lt;/em&gt; although that was near; for God said, Lest the people regret ( &lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; ) when they see war, and they return to Miẓrayim&quot;(Exodus 13:17). The motif of guidance repeats at the same chapter (verse 21): &quot;And the Lord went before them by day in a pillar of a cloud, to lead them ( &lt;strong&gt;l&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;nḥ&lt;/strong&gt;** ot &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; m&lt;strong&gt;) the way; and by night in a pillar of fire to give them light, that they might go by day and night&quot;. The order of the journeys was &quot;they departe/removed from X…. and they pitched (&lt;/strong&gt;v &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; y &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; n&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;u&lt;/em&gt;) at Y&quot;: guidance - **h **&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; nḥ &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; y &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; h** - (through the lillar of smoke and of fire) and then camping - &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ **a&lt;/strong&gt; n &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; y &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; h&lt;strong&gt;. (And we learn that the inspiration of the Torah to Moshe occurred only when the children of Israel campted (&lt;/strong&gt;ḥ &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; n &lt;strong&gt;**u&lt;/strong&gt; ) and found rest ( &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;** u &lt;strong&gt;**ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ). Only then the Levites erected the Tabernacle and Moshe could enter to the innermost chamber to the dwelling (Shekhinah) of God and then hear &quot;the voice speaking to him from off the covering that was upon the ark of testimony, from between the two keruvim: and it spke to him&quot; (Numbers 7:89).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\&amp;lt;\&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;**  - Laying&lt;strong&gt;(&lt;/strong&gt;h &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; n &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; h&lt;strong&gt;) and&lt;/strong&gt; Landing&lt;strong&gt;(&lt;/strong&gt;n &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;**it&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is written about Adam &quot;And the Lord God (YHWH Elohim) took the man (adam), and put him (vayaniḥehu) into the garden of Ẹden&quot; (Gen. 2:15) - he was put by God inside the perfect environment that has been previously been prepared for him, though for the need &quot;to till it and to keep it&quot;. Noa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  too was put, as if laid, into the special environment – but this time it was an artificial ecological environment. an &quot;Ecosystem&quot;, that had been built by Noah and his sons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  was also the first man to land ( &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;** a &lt;strong&gt;**ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;** a &lt;strong&gt;**t&lt;/strong&gt; ) from his vessel to the renewed (&quot;terraformed&quot;) earth. Landing is a sort of descent and fall, and we shall see the landing down of  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;  in the drunkenness and the inferiority ( &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; i &lt;strong&gt;tut&lt;/strong&gt; ) of  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;**   &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt;  Sacrificial Offering&lt;strong&gt;(&lt;/strong&gt;M &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; nḥ &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; h**)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon exiting the Ark,  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  made another building operation: &quot;and  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  built an altar to the Lord; and took of every clean beast, and of every clean bird, and offered burnt offerings on the altar&quot; (8:20).  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  appears here as a priest who brings sacrifices, and one (in contradistinction to Qayin) whose sacrifice was accepted. From here on the issue of sacrifices and offerings will reappear hundreds of times in the Torah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From **&lt;/strong&gt; N &lt;strong&gt;oa&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;** to **&lt;/strong&gt; N &lt;strong&gt;e&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;e&lt;/strong&gt; mi &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; h**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole passage of the Torah and the Prophets goes between these two builders - from the building of the Ark by  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  and his sons to the collective building of the walls of Jerusalem under the direction of  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;mi&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;. Inside the box of the walls of Jerusalem the Temple was rebuilt as the place of safeguarding and editing of the Torah through  &lt;strong&gt;Ẹzra&lt;/strong&gt;  the scribe and his entourage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In between we find  &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;** o &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;, the father of Samson, who is the prototype of the victorious Messiah. As for the name of the last Messiah, there are many conjectures, but the most common is that his name would be ** M **e&lt;/strong&gt; n &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;e&lt;/strong&gt; m** (comforter).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; ,  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  and  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;** in &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; h**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After God repented ( &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; i &lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt;** n &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ &lt;strong&gt;e&lt;/strong&gt; m&lt;strong&gt;) that He has created humankind and decided to destroy them, he had mercy (&lt;/strong&gt;ḥ &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; n &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; n&lt;strong&gt;) toward Noaḥ - the one who &quot;found grace (&lt;/strong&gt;Ḥ &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; n&lt;strong&gt;) in the eyes of the Lord&quot; (Gen. 6:8). The virtue of Noah brought out the divine qualities of being merciful (&lt;/strong&gt;ḥ &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; n &lt;strong&gt;**un&lt;/strong&gt; ) and compassionate ( &lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;** um**).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sentence &quot;and  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;oa&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  found  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; is an obvious and intended word play. &quot; &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; is &quot; &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; spelled backward. The word &quot; &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; is commonly explained as the acronym of &quot; &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;k&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; _ _ &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;st&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; (Hidden Wisdom) or &lt;strong&gt;ח&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;&quot;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ן&lt;/strong&gt; (and there are also those explaining it as &quot; &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;o&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;k&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;t&lt;/strong&gt; _ _ &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;s&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;im&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; (Feminine Wisdom).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As noted in the chapter, the Gematria value of  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  (who is &quot;husbandman of the Adamah&quot;, the living Earth; Gen. 9:20) is 58, which is also the Gematria value of &quot; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;G&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; – the known garden, the Garden of  &lt;strong&gt;Ẹd&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Name Noaḥ ** ( **נוח ** - with full spelling) and  **the number 64&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, the name is generally spelled in its full form as  &lt;strong&gt;No&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  -  &lt;strong&gt;נוח&lt;/strong&gt;. This name (in its full spelling, with the addition of the letter W'aw (ו), which is one of the letters of the Name of YHWH) has the Gematria value of 64 (the full number of situations in the Chinese I-Ching or &quot;Book of Changes&quot;; whereas in the Qabbalah by Gematria S'D ( &lt;strong&gt;ס&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; &lt;strong&gt;ד&lt;/strong&gt; ) – the common acronym of &quot; &lt;strong&gt;Siạt&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h d&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;y&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; (Divine Help). This Gematria value is equal to that of &quot; &lt;strong&gt;Ad&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;  ve &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;v&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; (Adam and Eve) – with Noah there is a new beginning to humankind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We find the word spelled this way only once in the Torah: &quot;And the Lord came down in a cloud, and spoke to him, and took of the spirit that emenated upon him, and gave it to the seventy elders; and it came to pass that when the spirit rested upon them ( &lt;strong&gt;k&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;'&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;** o &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; ḥ** &lt;em&gt;ạleyhem haruaḥ),&lt;/em&gt; they prophesied, but continued not&quot; (Numbers 11:25).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spirit that emanated upon Moshe also alighted ( &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ) upon the seventy elders of Israel. Likewise, &quot;And when the sons of the prophets who were in  &lt;strong&gt;Y&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;riḥo&lt;/strong&gt;  (Jericho) saw him, they said, The spirit of Eliyahu (Elijah) rests ( &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ) on Elisha; And they came to meet him, and bowed themselves to the grouond before him&quot; (II Kings 2:15). And similarly: &quot;And there shall come forth a rod of the stem of Yishay, and a branch shall grow out of his roots; and the spirit of the Lord shall rest ( &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ) upon him, the spirit of wisdom and understanding, the spirit of counsel and might, the spirit of knowledge and of the fear of the Lord&quot; (Isaiah 11:1). There is a passage of the spirit of prophecy through a stage of &quot; &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;&quot;, of rest ( &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;** u &lt;strong&gt;**ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; ) and passivity.1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name, or the principle, of &quot; &lt;strong&gt;No&lt;/strong&gt;'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; ( &lt;strong&gt;נוח&lt;/strong&gt; ) is as result from the entry of the penetration of the W'aw of the holy spirit into the passive state of  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number 64 is a significant number in its own right: 64 = 2^6 = 4^3 = 8^2, namely the number of square cells in a flat square of 8, like a chess board; the number of cubical cells in a box of 4x4x4 (and also the number of 6D cells of a 6D hypercube of 2x2x2x2x2x2). 64 is the number of world-year-soul states which are at the basis of the Taoist world-view and the I-Ching book, where they are represented by the 64 hexagrams. These 64 states are generally presented on the plane, in the form of 8x8, but these 64 states can also be arrayed in a cube of 4x4x4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number 64 has connection to the fourth &quot;perfect Number (apparently the largest perfect number known in antiquity), which is 8128: 127 x 64 = 8,128. So, this perfect number is the product of the spatial principle of 64 and of another principle expressed by the number 127. We shall meet this number later, in the Parasha of  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ye&lt;/strong&gt; _ _ &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; , where we shall be able to appreciate the appearance of the fourth perfect number related to the cave of  &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;k&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;pel&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;  (multiplication) in &lt;strong&gt;Qiryat Arbạ&lt;/strong&gt; (City of the Four).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The  &lt;strong&gt;Name&lt;/strong&gt;  &quot; &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  is the &quot;second round&quot; of Adam. In the first deed of Adam, he composed names (Shemot) to all the animals, whereas the first creation of  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; o'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; , his firstborn, he called &quot; &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;&quot;, namely &quot;Name&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name &quot; &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; is a root to the letters of  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;s&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;ha&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;נשמה&lt;/strong&gt; ) – the Eternal or Over Soul. It is there between the letters  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; un ( &lt;strong&gt;נ&lt;/strong&gt;  or ** ן** ) - that signifies the Sephirah of  &lt;strong&gt;Bin&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; (&quot;the 50 {' &lt;strong&gt;נ&lt;/strong&gt; } Gates of  &lt;strong&gt;Bin&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; {Understanding}; and the lower  &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;'e { &lt;strong&gt;ה&lt;/strong&gt; } of the name of  &lt;strong&gt;YHWH&lt;/strong&gt; , representing the Shekhinah and the World of Action. The connection between  &lt;strong&gt;Bin&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; {Understanding} and Action is through The Name -  &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; ), which means that to comprehend and understand the components and procedures of action, one needs to give them names that explain them and that combine to a full explanation, (the Higher Knowledge - &lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a'&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ạt Ẹlyon&lt;/strong&gt; ).2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest value of contemporary Judaism is &quot; &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; ( &lt;strong&gt;השם&lt;/strong&gt; ), which is the reverse order of the letters of the name &quot; &lt;strong&gt;M&lt;/strong&gt; o &lt;strong&gt;s&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; (Moses –  &lt;strong&gt;משה&lt;/strong&gt; ). In the Torah of Moshe, the divine name is of  &lt;strong&gt;YHWH&lt;/strong&gt;. Present day Jews do not dare to pronounce the explicit Name and call it &quot; &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; (meaning literally &quot;The Name&quot;).  It is said (in Naḥmanides' (&lt;em&gt;Ramban&lt;/em&gt;) Torah commentary and in the Book of Zohar) that the whole entire Torah is the expanded Great Name of the Holy One. Therefore, also whoever reads aloud the Torah (&lt;em&gt;qore baTorah&lt;/em&gt;) in truth, for its own sake (&lt;em&gt;Torah lishmah&lt;/em&gt;) – (s)he is calling the divinity in her full name (&lt;em&gt;Shem haMeforash&lt;/em&gt;) and may receive the answer of the Holy One.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let us look at the significance coded in the sum of the Gematria values of Noah and his sons: No'aḥ  58 + Shem  340 + Ḥam  48 + Yefet  490 = 936. The number 936, in turn 936 = 26 x 36. As we've already seen, 26 signifies the Name of  &lt;strong&gt;YHWH&lt;/strong&gt; , whereas 36 signifies the array of &quot; &lt;strong&gt;El&lt;/strong&gt; eh&quot; ( &lt;strong&gt;אלה&lt;/strong&gt; ) – the manifest parts of God ( &lt;strong&gt;El&lt;/strong&gt; o &lt;strong&gt;him&lt;/strong&gt; ).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Academies of Shem and Ẹver&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The midrashim3tell of Noah's descendants  &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;  and  &lt;strong&gt;Ẹv&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt;  as if they held an academy (&lt;em&gt;Beit Midrash&lt;/em&gt;) where they taught the  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  – the hidden wisdom of the Sons of Noah, especially the secrets of the Hebrew names –  &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;mot&lt;/strong&gt; _ _ &lt;strong&gt;Ịvr&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;yim&lt;/strong&gt;  – and the Hebrew letters –  &lt;strong&gt;Ot&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;yot&lt;/strong&gt; _ _ &lt;strong&gt;Ịvr&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;io&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;yot&lt;/strong&gt;. This amounts to a  &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;** i&lt;strong&gt;-Semantic study place (&lt;em&gt;Beit Midrash&lt;/em&gt;) that uses a universal language, assembled from all the world's languages and finds parallels among the diverse names, which is also a Hebrew exegesis – **M **&lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; dr &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; s &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;h _** Ịv ****r**** i ** - that is based on Hebrew Language - ** Ịvr **_i&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; t**_ _– as a universal esoteric language and searches to find the secrets that issue from the Hebrew letters, words and names. This operation may lead to the realization of the prophecy of Ẓephanyah &quot;For then I will convert the people to a purer language&quot;. This will be the rectification to the confusion of languages of Babel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By Gematria, &quot; &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt; he &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; + &quot; &lt;strong&gt;Ẹv&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt;&quot;  340 + 272 = 612 (as the 613 commands minus one), which is also the Gematria value of  &lt;strong&gt;Brit&lt;/strong&gt;  – covenant. To the extent that the Noahide dispensation may get accepted in the world, the pupils of the future academy of Shem and Ẹver would likely be allies to Israel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entire appendix may conceivably be regarded as a sample lesson of a modern incarnation of the Academy of Shem and Ẹver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have started this article noting Rabbi &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;ḥm&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; (Nachman) of Breslow's claim that the letters of  &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;  ( &lt;strong&gt;ח&quot;ן&lt;/strong&gt; ) have the capacity to bring the prayer to be accepted. We may end by pointing to the phenomenon of his adherents writing the name &quot;Noaḥ&quot; as graffiti on walls all over Israel as a sign of the Times:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;                 **N** a -  **N** a **ḥ**  -  **N** a **ḥ**** m ** - ** N **a** ḥ ****m** a **n**  -  **N** a **ḥ**** m **a** n ** ** m **&amp;amp;#39;** Um **a** n**
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{Article viewed  &lt;strong&gt;4875&lt;/strong&gt;  times between 12.04.2010 and 1.1.19}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes:
[1] Already the Sages observed the special character of the letters  &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;'e and  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;'un, in that they are &quot;letters that have no coupling (Zivug)&quot; (whereas Aleph + Tet = Bet + Ḥet = Gimmel + Zayin = 10, and likewise with the letters Y'ud till Ẓadi). Therefore, their coupling is with &quot;the aid of the Name (&lt;em&gt;be'ẹzrat haShem&lt;/em&gt;)&quot;, which connects them to form &quot; &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; e &lt;strong&gt;s&lt;/strong&gt; ha &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;&quot; ( &lt;strong&gt;נשמה&lt;/strong&gt; )&quot; - oversoul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#
The Hebrew word for both &quot;spirit&quot; and &quot;wind&quot; (and also direction) is  &lt;strong&gt;Ru&lt;/strong&gt;'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;. The  &lt;strong&gt;Ru&lt;/strong&gt;'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  moves within the 3-dimensional space, which is symbolized by the Hebrew letter  &lt;strong&gt;W&lt;/strong&gt;'aw ( &lt;strong&gt;ו&lt;/strong&gt; ), whose numerical value is 6 and is used to signify the six main directions of the 3D space. Thus, there is &quot;a storm wind ( &lt;strong&gt;Ru&lt;/strong&gt;'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; ) coming out of the north&quot; (Ezekiel 1:4), and also &quot;Come from the four winds ( &lt;strong&gt;Ru&lt;/strong&gt;' &lt;strong&gt;ḥot&lt;/strong&gt; ), O spirit ( &lt;strong&gt;Ru&lt;/strong&gt;'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; ) and breathe upon those slain, that they may live&quot; (Ez. 37:9). But we also learn from Elijah &quot;And He said, Go out, and stand upon the mountain before the Lord (YHWH) And behold, the Lord passed by, and a great and strong wind ( &lt;strong&gt;Ru&lt;/strong&gt;'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; ) rent the mountain and broke the rocks in pieces before the Lord; but the Lord was not in the wond ( &lt;strong&gt;Ru&lt;/strong&gt;'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; ); and after the wind an earthquake, but the Lord was not in the earthquake; and after the earthquake a fire, but the Lord was not in the fire; and after the fire a still small voice&quot;(1 Kings 19:11) – only when the whole noise {which derives from the mental state of the prophesier} rests, then the spirit lands to rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#
E.g. Midrash &lt;em&gt;Bereshit Raba&lt;/em&gt; 63, on &lt;em&gt;vayitroẓeẓu habanim&lt;/em&gt;; shir haShirim Midrash Raba, section 6.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">the-names-of-noah-and-his-sons</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Appendix 2-B: Some Secrets Of The Ark And The Ẓohar</title><link href="/blog/2010/03/12/appendix-2-b-some-secrets-of-the-ark-and-the-zohar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Appendix 2-B: Some Secrets Of The Ark And The Ẓohar" /><published>2010-03-12T07:05:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-03-12T07:05:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/2010/03/12/appendix-2-b-some-secrets-of-the-ark-and-the-zohar</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2010/03/12/appendix-2-b-some-secrets-of-the-ark-and-the-zohar.html">&lt;p&gt;some-secrets-of-the-ark-and-the-zohar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-b-some-secrets-of-the-ark-and-the-ẓohar&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2-B: Some SECRETS OF THE ARK and THE ẒOHAR&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yitzḥaq Ḥayut-Man&lt;/strong&gt; _ 14.04.2010_&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;|   |
| — |&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;|   |
| — | — |&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Re-GENESIS Project,  &lt;strong&gt;Appendix 2-B&lt;/strong&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-secrets-of-noaḥs-ark-and-the-ẓohar&quot;&gt;Some Secrets of Noaḥ's Ark and the Ẓohar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.&lt;/strong&gt;** Connections between the Ark and the Tabernacle**&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The building of Noaḥ's Ark, thought the Sages, parallels not only the Creation of the World, but also the building of the Tabernacle and the Temple of Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us recall the specific commands that Noaḥ received: “Make thee an ark of Gofer wood; rooms shalt thou make in the ark, and shalt pitch it within and without with pitch. And this is the fashion of which thou shalt make it; the length of the ark shall be three hundred cubits, the breadth of it fifty cubits, and the height of it thirty cubits. A window (Ẓohar) shalt thou make to the ark, and to a cubit shalt thou finish it above; and the door of the ark shalt thou set in its side; with lower, second and third stories shalt thou make it” (6:14-16). That is, the thirty cubits of the height of the ark were divided to three stories, likely equal in height, namely: each story ten cubits high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most significant and canonical building mentioned in the Torah was the building of the Tabernacle. We have shown that, compared with 34 verses that were required for the Torah to describe all the works of Creation, the description of the Tabernacle and its construction required 256 (4**4) verses. “Issues of Torah are poor at their place and rich in another place” (&lt;em&gt;Tosafot, Kritut&lt;/em&gt; page 14a). By comparing with the pattern of the Tabernacle and its construction we might understand better the matter of the ark:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The proportions of the long and narrow ark are reminiscent of the Planks of the Tabernacle. These planks were of 10 x 1.5 x 1 cubits, whereas the Ark had the size of 300 x 50 x 30 cubits, that is a proportion of 10:1.67:1 cubit (the difference between 1.67 and 1.5 can be explained by the need to use whole or simple numbers to describe building elements).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The floor plan of the ark – three hundred by fifty cubits – contains three times the yard of the Tabernacle: hundred by fifty cubits (Exodus 27:19).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The basic module of the Tabernacle is the cube of 10 x 10 x 10 cubits of the Holy of Holies. All the measures of the Ark are multiples of 10, so that it is possible to divide the ark to the module of the Tabernacle. The entire space of the ark contains 450 such modules (300 x 50 x 30 cubits) – which are ten times  &lt;strong&gt;Ad&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt;  by Gematria, a motive we shall return to.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The image ( &lt;strong&gt;Ẓ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;l&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; ) of Adam – and the Image of He in whose Image and likeness was Adam formed – the Image of God – is also made of three stories: the top one parallels the head (brain), the middle one parallels the chest (heart), and the lower one parallels the belly (liver –  &lt;strong&gt;K&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;v&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;d&lt;/strong&gt; ). This is much like the ark, whose top floor presumably served for the dwelling of the humans (the brain), the middle floor served the dwellings of the animals (the heart of the mission) whereas the bottom floor served for utilities and food stores (the liver and belly) and the collection (and perhaps recycling) of wastes. The Tabernacle (and the Temple that derived from it) allows seeing a similar division: the measures of the Tabernacle edifice were 30 x 10 x 10 cubits, which derive from the addition of the Holy of Holies (whose form, as noted, is cubical) and the Holy ( &lt;strong&gt;Qod&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;s&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;, and in the Temple, the  &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;ik&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;ha&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;l&lt;/strong&gt; ), whose form is of a box (Exodus 26:33). This Holy, whose measure (at Solomon's Temple) is the measure of two Ark stories, parallels the belly and the chest (and the seven lower Sefirot), and the Holy of Holies parallels the head (and the three higher Sefirot). The assignment of places in the ark recalls the four degrees of being according to the Kabbalah – mineral, vegetal, animal and verbal (namely humans) and Judah haLevi, in his book “the Kuzari”, adds another degree – the “prophetic”, which is the potential degree of the people of Israel. The mineral in the ark served the construction material, the (stored) vegetal matches the lower floor, the animal match the middle floor and the verbal match the higher floor – where the glazed Tzohar at the ceiling of the ark symbolizes the flow of prophecy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another connection, this time semantic and not numeric, is between this  &lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;v&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; -Ark and the “the Ark of the Covenant” that the Tablets of the Covenant were laid in, and the temporary heir to the Tabernacle and the Temple – namely the Synagogue – where there is also laid a Torah scroll inside an “Ark”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, a Torah is housed in a ** T** &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;v&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; -Ark, same with the five Books of Moses in the synagogue Ark&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ark of Noaḥ, the ark/box of papyrus of Moses and the sacred Ark inside any synagogue pertain to the same pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. The Ark and the Tzohar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one element in Noaḥ's Ark that it is not clear whether it is functional or symbolic (or both), which is the Tzohar). As  &lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt; oa &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  was told: “A window - Tzohar – shalt thou make to the ark, and to a cubit shalt thou finish it above” (Gen. 6:16). These are somewhat obscure words and the interpreters have proposed several explanations. Rashi posits two possibilities: “Some say window and some say a precious stone that gives them light” (as also in Midrash Bereshit Raba). Ibn Ẹzra explains “Tzohar” as “a place through which the light enters, and is a derivative of Tzohorayim” (noontime – that is, the time that the sunlight equally to the East and to the West). Whereas Rabenu Beḥaye explains that this was a precious stone called &lt;em&gt;Bareqet&lt;/em&gt; (Carbuncle) that was used in the Ḥoshen (the High Priest's breast plate) for the Tribe of Levi and which the prophet called “Eqdaḥ”, is it was said “And I will make thy windows (of the New Jerusalem) of rubies, and thy gates of Eqdaḥ (beryl) stones, and all thy borders of choicest stones” (Isaiah 54:12). The objection among the interpreters to the explanation that it is the window is that a window one cubit long would not suffice to light up a closed ark 300 cubits long, so that there must have been other windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Ḥassidic interpretation that adds and builds upon the explanation of the Ba'ạl Shem Tov that the Tevah (Ark) is the word of prayer, is from Rabbi Elimelekh, that it merits the person praying that the prayer word that issues from the mouth shall be as beautiful as the precious stone of the Tzohar. Such Ḥassidic interpretations accord with the modern Hebrew meaning of “ &lt;strong&gt;Ẓ&lt;/strong&gt; o &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt;” as “ &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;ẓh&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt;”, namely an obligating statement of principle.7&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that the Tzohar has to do with light – and especially with a light called “Zohar”, about which it was prophesied “And they who are wise shall shine like the brightness (Zohar) of the firmament” (Daniel 12:3) and in greater detail in Ezekiel, “And I Then I beheld , and lo, a likeness as the appearance of fire; from what appeared to be his loins downward, fire; and from his loins upward, as it were the appearance of brightness (Zohar), something like electrum ( &lt;strong&gt;Ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;s&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;m&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;l&lt;/strong&gt;  – the modern Hebrew word for electricity) (8:2). The Tzohar is connected with the precious stone of the tribe of Levi and therefore with the functions of the Tabernacle and the Temple. It is possible to associate the story of the incarcerated in an ark with just one window to Plato's “parable of the Cave”, according to which people see only the “reflected light” – they do not perceive the reality but only its shadows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, the Kabbalah makes distinction between “Or Yashar” (direct light), which is the original light, and “Or Ḥozer” (reflected light) by which we observe the different objects, and the direct light is the better.[2] It may be said that Plato's “parable of the Cave” actually asserts that our deficiency as humans is in being bound through the physical (3D) world to see only reflected light and not the original direct light. And here the quality and the function of the Ẓohar of the ark (whether as a window or a precious stone) is to transfer the direct light into the dark cavern of the ark, which is like the belly of the whale of Jonah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Habitually we see only light reflected from objects and not the original light. Nowadays we are moving from learning and observation of reflected light to those of direct light. Looking at TV and computer screens, at which millions of people spend many hours, we observe emitted light (Or Yoẓe). The letters, pictures and visual patterns that appear to each person off the computer screen are made of “direct light” that comes from the screen to the eye and brain of the reader, and not from reflected light off book pages. This has something of the quality of the appearance of the Torah “in black fire over a white fire”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a reasonable interpretation that the “Tzohar” means a decorated, stained glass window built from sections of colored glass and prisms (a general form of the cutting of precious stones) that creates a pattern of lights – whether figurative, abstract-geometrical or letters of light. Thus in this portion there is a premonition, perhaps prophetic, of an element that would become extremely important in temple architecture, including in the Dome of the Rock and in Gothic Cathedrals (which can be regarded as derivatives of the Dome of the Rock). The theoretician and pioneer of the stained glass windows was Suger, Abbot of St. Denis, who emphasized the quality of “Lux Continua”, which is the divine light that contains and surrounds all. His objective was to form “walls of light” within the cathedral and thereby to reproduce the light of the Heavenly Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suger wrote expressly that he invited artisans from Byzantium and from Moslem countries. Likewise, the Qabbalah makes distinction between “Or Yashar” (direct light), which is the original light, and “Or Ḥozer” (reflected light) by which we observe the different objects, and the direct light is the better.[2] It may be said that Plato's “parable of the Cave” actually asserts that our deficiency as humans is in being bound through the physical (3D) world to see only reflected light and not the original direct light. And here, the quality and the function of the Ẓohar of the ark (whether as a window or a precious stone) is to transfer the direct light into the dark cavern of the ark, which is like the belly of the whale of Jonah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Habitually we see only light reflected from objects and not the original light. Nowadays we are moving from learning and observation of reflected light to those of direct light. Looking at TV and computer screens, at which millions of people spend many hours, we observe emitted light (Or Yotẓe). The letters, pictures and visual patterns that appear to each person off the computer screen are made of “direct light” that comes from the screen to the eye and brain of the reader, and not from reflected light off book pages. This has something of the quality of the appearance of the Torah “in black fire over a white fire”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gothic architecture presented the possibility of building actual shrines of light. Nowadays technology allows the building of entire structures of steel that are mainly glazing, such as the Geodesic Domes of Buckminster Fuller, including his vision to build a dome that would form a ball of lights that presents the whole planet earth and its various trends as patterns of light points. In the Revelation of John that concludes the Christian Bible there is a vision of “the Sea of Glass” over Jerusalem, upon which there take place epiphanies of the Messiah among 24 Elders of Israel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes:
[1] One should note the wonderful article of the RaShaZ, the Alte Rebbe about “&lt;em&gt;vesamti Kodkod shimshotayikh&lt;/em&gt;” (And I will make thy windows of rubies) see Liqute Torah for Re'eh, pages 24d-29a, that render what is mentioned here and more, in greater depth and extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] The Kabbalah and Kabbalah scholarship literature about light is immense. Much treatment of the subject may be found in Moshe Idel's “Absorbing Perfections”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;-&quot;&gt;-&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This concept is examined in detail by the Maharal, &lt;em&gt;Be'er haGolah&lt;/em&gt; V3, 12&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chapters in the Bible where later, Christian divisions and they do not oblige the Jewish reading. Many portions (&lt;em&gt;Parashot&lt;/em&gt;) start or end in the middle of a chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The claim that Israel, and specifically Zion, are the Nation of God and co-creators with Him of the New Heavens and New Earth is given clearly in the introduction to the (book of) Zohar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hebrew word for both “spirit” and “wind” (and also direction) is  &lt;strong&gt;Ru&lt;/strong&gt;'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;. The  &lt;strong&gt;Ru&lt;/strong&gt;'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt;  moves within the 3-dimensional space, which is symbolized by the Hebrew letter  &lt;strong&gt;W&lt;/strong&gt;'aw ( &lt;strong&gt;ו&lt;/strong&gt; ), whose numerical value is 6 and is used to signify the six main directions of the 3D space. Thus, there is “a storm wind ( &lt;strong&gt;Ru&lt;/strong&gt;'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; ) coming out of the north” (Ezekiel 1:4), and also “Come from the four winds ( &lt;strong&gt;Ru&lt;/strong&gt;' &lt;strong&gt;ḥot&lt;/strong&gt; ), O spirit ( &lt;strong&gt;Ru&lt;/strong&gt;'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; ) and breathe upon those slain, that they may live” (Ez. 37:9). But we also learn from Elijah “And He said, Go out, and stand upon the mountain before the Lord (YHWH) And behold, the Lord passed by, and a great and strong wind ( &lt;strong&gt;Ru&lt;/strong&gt;'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; ) rent the mountain and broke the rocks in pieces before the Lord; but the Lord was not in the wond ( &lt;strong&gt;Ru&lt;/strong&gt;'a &lt;strong&gt;ḥ&lt;/strong&gt; ); and after the wind an earthquake, but the Lord was not in the earthquake; and after the earthquake a fire, but the Lord was not in the fire; and after the fire a still small voice”(1 Kings 19:11) – only when the whole noise {which derives from the mental state of the prophesier} rests, then the spirit lands to rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E.g. Midrash &lt;em&gt;Bereshit Raba&lt;/em&gt; 63, on &lt;em&gt;vayitroẓeẓu habanim&lt;/em&gt;; shir haShirim Midrash Raba, section 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7For example, the Revisionist-Ẓionist leader Ze'ev Zabotinsky, who was a poet and an artist of the Hebrew language, called for a new (re-)vision of Ẓionism and named the movement “Brit ha &lt;strong&gt;Tz&lt;/strong&gt; o &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;strong&gt;r&lt;/strong&gt;” as an acronym of “ &lt;strong&gt;h&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Ẓ&lt;/strong&gt;** ionut &lt;strong&gt;_ &lt;em&gt;** h **_a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; R &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; visionisti**&lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8  The term “Servant Nation” was coined by Hugh Schonfield; see Appendix 1-D - The Servant Nation in the Haphtarah of the Genesis portion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">some-secrets-of-the-ark-and-the-zohar</summary></entry></feed>